<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Salt upon salt: made out of certain ingenious verses upon the late storm and the death of His Highness ensuing. By which contemplative object, occasion is taken, to offer to consideration the probable neer approaching of greater storms, and more sad consequences. / By Geo. Wither, Esquire.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1827_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863800</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116015</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116015)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 228:E1827[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Salt upon salt: made out of certain ingenious verses upon the late storm and the death of His Highness ensuing. By which contemplative object, occasion is taken, to offer to consideration the probable neer approaching of greater storms, and more sad consequences. / By Geo. Wither, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for L. Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659 [i.e. 1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>His Highness = Oliver Cromwell.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug."; the '9' in imprint date is crossed out and replaced with '8'.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116015:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Salt upon Salt: Made out of certain INGENIOUS VERSES Upon the Late STORM And the Death of His HIGHNESS Enſuing.</p>
            <p>By which <hi>Contemplative Object,</hi> Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is taken, to offer to Conſideration the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable neer approaching of greater <hi>Storms,</hi> and more ſad <hi>Conſequences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By GEO. WITHER, Eſquire.</p>
            <p>SALT <hi>ſeaſons all things,</hi> ſaving onely thoſe Which muſt feed <hi>Fiſhes, Maggots, Dogs</hi> and <hi>Crows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Read it, and heed it, For you need it; And ſo, God ſpeed it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>L. Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116015:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116015:2"/>
            <head>To the READER</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>OCcaſion</hi> from a <hi>trifling Object</hi> ſprings,</l>
               <l>Once more, to offer <hi>heed</hi> of <hi>ſerious Things.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, by peruſing ſome late printed <hi>Rimes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That, which may much concern the <hi>preſent Times,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was tender'd to my <hi>Thought;</hi> and what to me</l>
               <l>Was offer'd, ſhall to you now offer'd be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I began to know the <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I made <hi>Records</hi> of what I found them then,</l>
               <l>Continuing ever ſince, to take good heed,</l>
               <l>How they <hi>ſtood ſtill,</hi> went <hi>back,</hi> or did <hi>proceed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Till of my <hi>Scale of Time,</hi> aſcending Heav'n,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Round</hi> I ſtand on, maketh ten times <hi>Seven;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, being likely, now, ere long to leave them,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Memorandum,</hi> I intend to give them,</l>
               <l>Of what, <hi>this day,</hi> they do appear to me,</l>
               <l>As alſo, what they may here after be;</l>
               <l>(According as they ſhall direct their <hi>Courſe</hi>)</l>
               <l>That, whether they are <hi>better</hi> grown, or <hi>worſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It may be to <hi>GOD</hi>'s Honour <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>read,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(What ere beſals) when they and I, am dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:116015:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When in this <hi>Iſle</hi> my <hi>Muſes</hi> first were known,</l>
               <l>The heads of <hi>VICE</hi> were not ſo Monſtrous grown,</l>
               <l>(Nor then ſo numerous) as now they be;</l>
               <l>For, <hi>Cerberus</hi> in thoſe dayes had but three,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Hydra</hi> ſeven: At preſent, they are more</l>
               <l>In <hi>Number,</hi> and more <hi>Large,</hi> then heretofore:</l>
               <l>So that theſe <hi>Monſters,</hi> for whoſe overthrow</l>
               <l>I was ingag'd, nigh <hi>fifty yeers</hi> ago,</l>
               <l>Are grown ſo formidable, that, they make</l>
               <l>The <hi>Fortreſſes</hi> of <hi>Moral Vertue</hi> ſhake,</l>
               <l>And, yield at preſent, work enough to do,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Hercules,</hi> and Mighty <hi>Sampſon</hi> too.</l>
               <l>Yet I have loſt no Ground, but kept the <hi>Field;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And will, till I have <hi>Conquer'd,</hi> or am <hi>Kild:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, though ſome daily <hi>fall off,</hi> who pretended</l>
               <l>Adherence to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> which we defended,</l>
               <l>(And though my Elder Brethren do but flout me)</l>
               <l>I find an <hi>Unſeen Army,</hi> pitch'd about me,</l>
               <l>Which takes my Part, and will effect at length,</l>
               <l>That, which is far beyond my ſingle ſtrength:</l>
               <l>And, he, who dies, in making good his <hi>Place,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though he prevails not, <hi>dies without Diſgrace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Liſt,</hi> I enter not, with guileful Charms,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Humane Eloquence,</hi> nor with ſuch <hi>Arms</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Defenſive, or offenſive, as were brought</l>
               <l>By them, who have of late, our <hi>Battails</hi> fought;</l>
               <l>But onely with a <hi>Sling, Stones,</hi> and a <hi>Staff,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At which my <hi>Friends</hi> jeer, and my <hi>Foes</hi> do laugh;</l>
               <l>Yet (mark the Sequel) for, a day will come,</l>
               <l>That ſhall place <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the <hi>higheſt Room;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116015:3"/>
               <l>That, they who by their <hi>Brethren</hi> were envide,</l>
               <l>(Or by their <hi>Maſters</hi> wronged) ſhall be tride;</l>
               <l>That thoſe <hi>Poor People,</hi> who oppreſſed be,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Body,</hi> or in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſhall be free;</l>
               <l>And, that, though this be ſcorn'd, it ſhall be ſed</l>
               <l>Whilſt I am <hi>Living,</hi> or, when I am <hi>Dead,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That, by thoſe, now-contemned <hi>Pebble-ſtones,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which I have flung, there will be <hi>Broken-Bones,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Bruiſed Braines,</hi> which did to ſome of thoſe.</l>
               <l>Prove Mortal, who have been my <hi>Countries</hi> Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean while, I'll proſecute what I intend,</l>
               <l>Not much regarding what a <hi>Foe,</hi> or <hi>Friend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall either <hi>Counter-act,</hi> or <hi>Counter-ſay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But, bear their <hi>Spights,</hi> and <hi>Cenſures as I may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor to my <hi>Theam</hi> will I ſo cloſe be tide,</l>
               <l>As not, ſometimes, to make a ſtep aſide,</l>
               <l>To take in that, which may conduce unto</l>
               <l>The <hi>Work,</hi> which I <hi>in chief,</hi> intend to do;</l>
               <l>But, act as my <hi>INSPIRER,</hi> moveth me:</l>
               <l>For, I'm by <hi>Him</hi> inſpir'd, not <hi>He</hi> by <hi>Me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And therefore, here, before I take my leave,</l>
               <l>I'll warn you, (leſt your thoughts I may deceive)</l>
               <l>That <hi>Method</hi> not to look for, which by thoſe</l>
               <l>Is uſed, who expreſs their Mindes in <hi>Proſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, Things, not in <hi>pre-meditated Thought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(To me upon a ſudden, being brought)</l>
               <l>I <hi>took in,</hi> as they came; and what they were</l>
               <l>Oft knew not, till in <hi>Words,</hi> they did appear:</l>
               <l>Which having ſignifi'd, you may thereby</l>
               <l>Gueſs, what to judge of them, as well, as I;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:116015:4"/>
               <l>And, whether, that ſhould not your hearts incline</l>
               <l>To think, there's ſomewhat in them more then <hi>Mine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laſt Year,</hi> I ſent a FLASH, which is let paſs,</l>
               <l>Unheeded, as a Thing that never was:</l>
               <l>Now follows the <hi>Report,</hi> or <hi>Clap of Thunder,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which have been <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>heard,</hi> thus far aſunder,</l>
               <l>To give the longer <hi>Warning;</hi> for the <hi>SHOT</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And THUNDER BOLT'S, (if <hi>Grace</hi> prevent them not)</l>
               <l>Will <hi>next year</hi> fly among you: GOD amend us,</l>
               <l>And, then, I am aſſur'd, He will defend us.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant and Remembrancer, <hi>GEORGE WITHER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection_of_poems">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116015:4"/>
            <head>SALT upon SALT: Made out of certain ingenious Verſes upon the late <hi>Storm,</hi> and the <hi>Death</hi> of His <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> enſuing; by which <hi>Contemplative Object,</hi> occaſion is taken to offer to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the probable neer approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of greater <hi>Storms,</hi> and more ſad <hi>Conſequences.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The ſaid <hi>Verſes</hi> are theſe that next follow, according to the <hi>Author's</hi> printed Copy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WE muſt reſign; heav'n his great <hi>Soul</hi> doth claims</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Storms</hi> as loud as his <hi>Immortal Fame;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His <hi>dying Groans,</hi> his <hi>laſt Breath</hi> ſhakes our <hi>Iſle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, Trees unout, fall for his <hi>Funeral-Pile;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>About his <hi>Palace,</hi> their broad Roots are toſt</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Air;</hi> ſo, <hi>Romulus</hi> was loſt;</l>
                  <l>So, <hi>New-Rome,</hi> in a <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> mist her <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from <hi>obeying,</hi> fell to <hi>worſhipping.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On <hi>Oeta's</hi> top, thus <hi>Hercules</hi> lay dead,</l>
                  <l>With ruin'd Oaks, and Vines about him ſpread:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, his laſt Furie, from the <hi>Mountain</hi> rent,</l>
                  <l>Our dying <hi>Hero,</hi> from the <hi>Continent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raviſh'd whole Towns, and Forts from <hi>Spaniards</hi> reft,</l>
                  <l>As his last Legacy to <hi>Britain</hi> left.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ocean,</hi> which our Hopes had long confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Could give no Limits to his vaſter Minde.</l>
                  <l>Our Bounds inlargement was his lateſt toil,</l>
                  <l>Nor hath he left us priſ'ners to this <hi>Iſle;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116015:5"/>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the <hi>Tropick,</hi> is, our Language ſpoke,</l>
                  <l>And Part of <hi>Flanders</hi> hath receiv'd our Yoke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From <hi>Civil-Broiles,</hi> he did us diſ-engage,</l>
                  <l>Found Nobler Objects for our Martial Rage,</l>
                  <l>And with wiſe Conduct, to His Country ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Antient Way</hi> of Conquering abroad.</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful then, if we no tears allow</l>
                  <l>To Him, who gave us <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Empire</hi> too.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Princes,</hi> who fear'd Him, griev'd, concern'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>No pitch of <hi>Glory,</hi> from the <hi>Grave</hi> is free:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nature</hi> herſelf, took notice of His Death,</l>
                  <l>And, ſighing, ſwel'd the <hi>Sea,</hi> with ſuch a Breath;</l>
                  <l>That, to remotest ſhoars, her Billows rowl'd,</l>
                  <l>Th'approaching <hi>Fate</hi> of her great <hi>Ruler</hi> told.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The <hi>Reſult,</hi> occaſioned by the preceding <hi>Theam.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Way with <hi>ſelf-reſpects;</hi> For now of late</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Private,</hi> and this <hi>Publick Weals</hi> Eſtate</l>
                  <l>Are much alike; and both of them, to me</l>
                  <l>Seem in this <hi>Criſis,</hi> at this day to be,</l>
                  <l>Threatning a <hi>Sudden Ruine,</hi> if much further</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Confuſion</hi> ſpreads, before reduc'd to Order.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Genius</hi> therefore, doth my Heart incline</l>
                  <l>To ſeek that <hi>Weal,</hi> whereon dependeth mine,</l>
                  <l>Leſt, whilſt for <hi>Private welfare,</hi> I endeavour,</l>
                  <l>That, and the <hi>Publick Peace,</hi> be loſt for ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This to prevent, (though ſome will think I dream)</l>
                  <l>There is <hi>occaſion</hi> couched in this <hi>Theam:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And (notwithſtanding, much it may be fear'd,</l>
                  <l>That, what it ſhall produce, will not be heard,</l>
                  <l>Among the <hi>tumults</hi> and <hi>confuſedneſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which now abound) it will have ſome Succeſs:</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116015:5"/>
                  <l>For, otherwhile, by <hi>Trifles,</hi> that is wrought,</l>
                  <l>Which could not by great <hi>Powers,</hi> to paſs be brought.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſmall ſhrill whiſtle,</hi> in a <hi>Storm,</hi> becoms</l>
                  <l>More ſignal then the beating of great <hi>Drums:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, who knows not, (he breathing thereinto)</l>
                  <l>What, by a <hi>Ramshorn Trumpet,</hi> GOD, may do?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our late <hi>loſs,</hi> doth on me to call begin,</l>
                  <l>As if I ſomewhat were concern'd therein,</l>
                  <l>And had a part to Act, wherein I may</l>
                  <l>Supply, at leaſt, a <hi>Fools part</hi> in the <hi>Play.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſince <hi>occaſion</hi> given there is none,</l>
                  <l>I, of my own accord have taken one,</l>
                  <l>Which, if a cauſleſs anger, it provoke</l>
                  <l>To miſchieve me, the care's already took;</l>
                  <l>I am too <hi>low a mark</hi> for <hi>Supreme Pow'rs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Too <hi>high,</hi> to dread an <hi>equal</hi> when he low'rs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>main prop,</hi> of this <hi>Government</hi> is gone,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Stone,</hi> our <hi>Maſter-builders</hi> built upon</l>
                  <l>Is now remov'd; and, either I miſtake,</l>
                  <l>Or, all that's built thereon begins to <hi>ſhake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And quite aſunder too, will fall at length,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs upheld, with more then <hi>humane ſtrength.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No former <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe <hi>Actions</hi> yeelded matter</l>
                  <l>So worthy of a <hi>Muſe</hi> that would not flatter,</l>
                  <l>Di'd at a time, wherein there liv'd ſo few</l>
                  <l>To give him that, which juſtly was his due,</l>
                  <l>(Without a <hi>diminution</hi> or <hi>exceſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Either of which, makes <hi>great things,</hi> to ſeem <hi>leſs</hi>)</l>
                  <l>For, having view'd moſt <hi>paper-monuments,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby the <hi>Fancie</hi> of this Age preſents</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Fame</hi> to memorie; I finde their <hi>Rimes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are ſo diſtracted, as if with theſe <hi>times</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Authors</hi> ſympathized in their <hi>wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And knew not what they <hi>meant,</hi> nor what they <hi>writ:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116015:6"/>
                  <l>Elſe, doubtleſs, none had fail'd ſo in expreſſing</l>
                  <l>His <hi>purpoſe,</hi> as to <hi>curſe,</hi> inſtead of <hi>bleſſing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he, whoſe <hi>Pcëm-elegiacal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is clos'd up, with the name of <hi>Jerubbaal.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some, ſo malitiouſly <hi>Invectives</hi> write,</l>
                  <l>As if their <hi>Pens,</hi> in Juice of <hi>Aconite</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were dipt (or rather in more venom'd matter)</l>
                  <l>So oppoſite to that, which they who <hi>flatter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hide underneath their <hi>tongues,</hi> that, in the ſtead</l>
                  <l>Of ſhewing hatred only to the <hi>dead,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They, <hi>living men</hi> impoyſon through the <hi>ear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When their <hi>uncharitable Charms</hi> they hear:</l>
                  <l>For, theſe have not alone in <hi>ſcurrile Verſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Blur'd him with what their malice could aſperſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>True,</hi> or <hi>untrue;</hi> but, alſo, take GOD's roome,</l>
                  <l>Dare to proncunce his <hi>everlasting Doome;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, wickedly, with <hi>Damned ſouls</hi> in Hell,</l>
                  <l>(As others do with <hi>Saints</hi>) him parallel:</l>
                  <l>Which argues an Intention, to defame</l>
                  <l>The <hi>perſon,</hi> though he merited no blame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some others, on that <hi>ſubject</hi> wantonize</l>
                  <l>As if their <hi>Muſe</hi> were hawking Butterflies:</l>
                  <l>Some, are all <hi>Oyl:</hi> ſome, have but this <hi>one fault,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The want of <hi>Sulphur, Mercurie,</hi> and <hi>Salt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, few of them, ſave he, whoſe <hi>lines preceding,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I make my <hi>Text,</hi> afford ought worth the reading:</l>
                  <l>And, they now put me into ſuch a <hi>fit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, if I have not much more <hi>Grace</hi> then <hi>wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It may to harſher <hi>Cenſures</hi> me expoſe</l>
                  <l>Then any one of them, yet undergoes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Except <hi>Obſcene Verſe,</hi> (and ſtrong lines, from whence</l>
                  <l>Are hardly ſcrew'd <hi>intelligible ſenſe</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strains</hi> like to this, theſe <hi>Times,</hi> beſt prize to praiſe;</l>
                  <l>And, 'tis a <hi>ſmart neat Peece,</hi> ΘΡΙΚΙΟΝ ſayes:</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116015:6"/>
                  <l>Which, I deny not; for, it mounts as high</l>
                  <l>As any <hi>Engliſh Pegaſus</hi> can flie,</l>
                  <l>And, is as <hi>well-pac'd:</hi> But he feels the Reins</l>
                  <l>Lie looſe upon his Creſt, and <hi>overstrains,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To know, what beſt the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> doth befit</l>
                  <l>With his <hi>own Ends,</hi> this <hi>Author</hi> wants not wit,</l>
                  <l>And, I believe, takes much more care then I,</l>
                  <l>What will beſt pleaſe, and wherewith to complie;</l>
                  <l>Though I, have more then forty years and five</l>
                  <l>Found, that my <hi>Courſe,</hi> is not the <hi>Courſe</hi> to thrive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Verſes,</hi> which to make my <hi>Theam</hi> I chuſe</l>
                  <l>Are but the <hi>ſportings,</hi> of their Authors <hi>Muſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſeem to me like <hi>Knacks</hi> which in a Hall,</l>
                  <l>I've ſeen hung up, for <hi>Flies</hi> to play withall.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are <hi>Wits</hi> bubbles, blown up with a Quill,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>watrie-Circles,</hi> with <hi>weak-Air</hi> doth fill;</l>
                  <l>Or, like a <hi>ſquib,</hi> which fires, and cracks, and flies,</l>
                  <l>And, makes a <hi>noiſe,</hi> that little ſignifies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, envie not his <hi>Fame,</hi> who is deceaſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor ought, whereby, it may be more encreaſt:</l>
                  <l>I, never ſuffred ought by his Diſpleaſure;</l>
                  <l>But, did enjoy his <hi>Favour,</hi> in ſome meaſure,</l>
                  <l>Which he knows, unto whom all things are known,</l>
                  <l>I, more employ'd for his <hi>weal,</hi> then mine <hi>own,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, diſadvantaged my <hi>ſelf,</hi> to do him</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>ſervices,</hi> as, I thought, I did owe him.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For theſe reſpects, none juſtly can ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>I grudge him ought, which may by <hi>Verſe</hi> or <hi>Proſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be added to his <hi>Fame;</hi> or, that the <hi>Mome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'll play, by carping, or detracting from</l>
                  <l>Another's contributions, if I ſee</l>
                  <l>They are in truth, what they may ſeem to be.</l>
                  <l>I, ſhould be pleaſ'd that thoſe <hi>Lines,</hi> which precede,</l>
                  <l>(With what elſe doth relate to him that's <hi>dead</hi>)</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116015:7"/>
                  <l>Whereby, ſome think, he may be honor'd much,</l>
                  <l>To all who hear, or view them, might prove ſuch,</l>
                  <l>That, no occaſion might from them be took,</l>
                  <l>Of what, to his diſhonour, will be ſpoke;</l>
                  <l>Or, to encreaſe thoſe <hi>Vanities</hi> which are</l>
                  <l>Already, multiplied, over far.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, therefore, now expect to be excuſ'd</l>
                  <l>Although at this time, I have nothing <hi>muſ'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, may concern him, in the <hi>common mode;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, in that <hi>place,</hi> he, now hath his abode</l>
                  <l>Where he regards not <hi>Bawbles. Praiſes,</hi> there,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Flatteries,</hi> no whit regarded are;</l>
                  <l>The moſt <hi>inchanting Charms,</hi> there, cannot charm him:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Detractions,</hi> or <hi>Invectives</hi> cannot harm him;</l>
                  <l>To write thoſe <hi>Truths,</hi> which might have done him ſhame</l>
                  <l>Whilſt here he liv'd; or gain'd the Writer blame,</l>
                  <l>Ought, now to be declar'd as well as thoſe</l>
                  <l>From whence his higheſt <hi>commendation</hi> flowes;</l>
                  <l>And, that may ſettle <hi>Peace,</hi> now being ſpoken,</l>
                  <l>Which in his life-time, might the <hi>Peace</hi> have broken.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>ſacred-Pen-men,</hi> future times acquaints,</l>
                  <l>Not only with the <hi>merits</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But alſo, with their <hi>Failings;</hi> and as great</l>
                  <l>By th'<hi>one,</hi> as th'other, is mans benefit:</l>
                  <l>For, which reſpect, I will not be afrayd:</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak, what to good purpoſe, may be ſayd;</l>
                  <l>Nor, from my <hi>Text</hi> (as now) to wheel about</l>
                  <l>To fetch in that, which others needleſs thought;</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Method,</hi> is not ſo much my intent,</l>
                  <l>As by good means, a <hi>miſchief,</hi> to prevent:</l>
                  <l>And, my <hi>digreſſions,</hi> may advance my end,</l>
                  <l>As much as that, which I did firſt intend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis now, high time, for us to ſpend our hours,</l>
                  <l>In gath'ring <hi>Fruits,</hi> and not in picking <hi>Flow's.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116015:7"/>
                  <l>I love to ſee <hi>truth,</hi> in her <hi>nakedneſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, ſhe ſhould ſometimes, put on a <hi>Dreſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſuch <hi>Poetick Flouriſhes</hi> adorn'd,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>ſafe</hi> may keep her, and from being <hi>ſcorn'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To which end, I my ſelf, compell'd have been</l>
                  <l>To mask and vail her, when I have foreſeen</l>
                  <l>Apparent <hi>Dangers;</hi> and another time</l>
                  <l>To cloath her, in that faſhionable <hi>Trim</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which moſt affect; that, there with brought acquainted,</l>
                  <l>True <hi>Beauty,</hi> may be known from what is painted.</l>
                  <l>And, that, they who were drawn in, by the <hi>Signe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might <hi>Gueſts</hi> be, for the goodneſs of the <hi>Wine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My Reverence to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> is not ſmall;</l>
                  <l>For, all true <hi>Poets</hi> are Prophetical,</l>
                  <l>And had a <hi>Preparation</hi> in the Womb,</l>
                  <l>Before they forth into the World did come;</l>
                  <l>Not, that their <hi>Faculty,</hi> ſhould be appli'd</l>
                  <l>To ſtir up <hi>Carnal Luſt,</hi> or puff up <hi>Pride;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, that they ſhould to <hi>Pietie</hi> invite,</l>
                  <l>And make <hi>Mankinde</hi> in <hi>Virtues</hi> more delight;</l>
                  <l>From which, prevaricating, they have loſt</l>
                  <l>Their Honour; and are quite deſpis'd almoſt.</l>
                  <l>They ſhould not ſtrive for words to pleaſe the ear,</l>
                  <l>In which, no <hi>ſolid Matter</hi> doth appear;</l>
                  <l>But, write ſo plainly, that, the <hi>meaneſt Wit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might from their <hi>Muſings,</hi> reap ſome benefit.</l>
                  <l>They ſhould not weave their <hi>Webs</hi> of <hi>Stuffs</hi> that be</l>
                  <l>So, diff'ring, that, they never can agree;</l>
                  <l>Nor, when our <hi>Sin,</hi> for <hi>Sober-Mourning</hi> calls,</l>
                  <l>Play us a <hi>Jigg,</hi> or ſing us <hi>Madrigals.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Meer verbal <hi>Whimſeys,</hi> in a <hi>Serious Cauſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which moſt part of the Readers more amaze</l>
                  <l>Then edifie; (by that which never was,</l>
                  <l>Nor is, nor ſhall <hi>hereafter come to paſs</hi>)</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116015:8"/>
                  <l>Look like ſolemnizing an <hi>Ordinance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Pious Duties,</hi> with a <hi>Morrice-Dance;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, like their actings, who, againſt the Forces</l>
                  <l>Of well-arm'd Foes, bring Troops of <hi>Hobby-horſes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What, in the <hi>Theam</hi> foregoing, is there ſaid</l>
                  <l>Which honours him deceaſed, if well weigh'd?</l>
                  <l>And hath not rather into queſtion brought</l>
                  <l>Things, which to queſtion, few men would have thought?</l>
                  <l>There, at his <hi>Death,</hi> a <hi>Storm,</hi> is fain'd to roar,</l>
                  <l>Which was o'er-blown almoſt a week before;</l>
                  <l>And, had it not been ſo, ſome would from thence</l>
                  <l>Have drawn, perhaps, an <hi>evil Conſequence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More <hi>Fancies,</hi> forming in the <hi>People's</hi> Brain,</l>
                  <l>Then two ſuch <hi>Storms,</hi> would have blown out again.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alluſions,</hi> too, are made, as if ſurmiz'd</l>
                  <l>That, He, henceforth ſhould be Idolatriz'd,</l>
                  <l>As more then <hi>Man,</hi> whom we this day perceive</l>
                  <l>Laid lower then the meaneſt Men that <hi>Live.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To teach us, that, in <hi>Princes,</hi> there's no truſt;</l>
                  <l>That, all meer <hi>Human-Glories,</hi> are but duſt;</l>
                  <l>And, that, <hi>Death</hi> will, their <hi>Vanity</hi> diſcover,</l>
                  <l>At whatſoe'er coſt, Double-Guilded over.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So, did His <hi>laſt Breath</hi> ſhake this <hi>Iſle</hi> of our,</l>
                  <l>As Pellets from a <hi>Pot-Gun,</hi> ſhake a <hi>Tow'r.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, all her <hi>Shakings,</hi> to my beſt perceiving,</l>
                  <l>Riſe from our own <hi>Diſtempers</hi> who are <hi>Living.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So, for his Funeral-Pile, un-cut Trees fell;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So,</hi> Romulus <hi>and He were Parallel;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So,</hi> New-Rome, <hi>in a Tempeſt, miſt her King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then, from obeying, fell to worſhipping;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, ſo, on</hi> Oeta, Hercules <hi>lay dead,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As <hi>Chalk</hi>'s like <hi>Cheeſe,</hi> and <hi>Beer</hi> is like to <hi>Bread.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So, from the Continent, He Towns hath torn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he, who teats a Hedge, and gets a Thorn</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116015:8"/>
                  <l>Which wounds his hand, and when he dreads no harm,</l>
                  <l>Doth gangrene, to the loſing of his Arm.</l>
                  <l>So, are our <hi>Freedoms,</hi> and our <hi>Bounds</hi> inlarg'd,</l>
                  <l>As his, who, from a <hi>ſmall Debt,</hi> is diſcharg'd,</l>
                  <l>To re-oblige himſelf, in that, which may</l>
                  <l>Sweep <hi>Liberty,</hi> and all he hath, away;</l>
                  <l>And, if our <hi>Endings</hi> prove like our <hi>Beginnings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Loſſes,</hi> vvill be greater then our <hi>Winnings.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What <hi>Comfort</hi> yields it, to impoſe a <hi>Yoke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On others, if our <hi>Fetters</hi> be not broke?</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Pleaſure</hi> brings it, if our <hi>Confines</hi> be</l>
                  <l>Inlarged, if in them, vve are not free?</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Profit,</hi> is it unto us at <hi>Home,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſome in <hi>Forraign Parts,</hi> inrich'd become,</l>
                  <l>If, vve mean vvhile are <hi>Beggars?</hi> or elſe more</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, impov'riſh'd, then we vvere before?</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Honour</hi> is it, that, both <hi>Tropicks</hi> hear</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Language,</hi> if to ſpeak <hi>Truth,</hi> few men dare?</l>
                  <l>Or vvhat by <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> vvill be got or ſav'd,</l>
                  <l>If they vvho <hi>Conquer'd,</hi> are at laſt inſlav'd?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not unto us, not unto us, be given,</l>
                  <l>(Or to our <hi>Chiefs</hi>) but to the GOD of Heaven,</l>
                  <l>The thanks and honour, that, both our <hi>Late Wars</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith Neighb'ring Foes, and our <hi>Domeſtick Jarrs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Super-added:</hi> VVould GOD, I could ſay,</l>
                  <l>VVere vvholly ended: (as I hope I may)</l>
                  <l>For, had not <hi>He,</hi> with our <hi>Protector</hi> ſtood,</l>
                  <l>VVe, till this day, had wallow'd in our Blood;</l>
                  <l>Yea, had not GOD, a <hi>timely ayd</hi> brought in,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroy'd long ſince, both <hi>He,</hi> and vve had bin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>Antient Way</hi> of Conquering <hi>abroad,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich this <hi>Muſe,</hi> doth implicitely applaud)</l>
                  <l>VVhat got vve by it, but a <hi>Curſed Game,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Atchiev'd vvith <hi>Blood,</hi> and loſt vvith <hi>Blood again?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116015:9"/>
                  <l>I know not vvhat the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a <hi>State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Policy</hi> by Law, may tolerate;</l>
                  <l>VVith that I vvill not meddle: But to me</l>
                  <l>It ſeemeth not to Quadrate or agree</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Moral Honeſty,</hi> or <hi>Sacred Laws,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Unleſs there be <hi>unqueſtionable Cauſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Pow'r apparent,</hi> vvhich doth vvarrantize</l>
                  <l>GOD's calling us to ſuch an Enterprize)</l>
                  <l>That, vve, into our Neighbours <hi>Lot,</hi> ſhould fall</l>
                  <l>VVith <hi>Fire and Sword;</hi> and Honourable call</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Deeds, for vvhich, LAVV, to their <hi>Actors</hi> gives</l>
                  <l>The ſtiles of <hi>Pyrats, Murtherers</hi> and <hi>Thieves:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, that, a few, ſhould vvithout free aſſent</l>
                  <l>Of all the <hi>People</hi> in a <hi>Parliament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ingage them by a <hi>Quarrel,</hi> which may coſt</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Lives,</hi> and all that may vvith <hi>Life</hi> be loſt:</l>
                  <l>I know no <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Goſpel,</hi> vvarranting</l>
                  <l>So hazzardous or reaſonleſs a thing;</l>
                  <l>Or, that, vve vvho ſubjection do profeſs</l>
                  <l>Unto the King of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should take the <hi>Wages,</hi> and the <hi>Colours</hi> carry</l>
                  <l>Of him, that's both His and our Adverſary.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I underſtand, how vve then do</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As we would willingly be done unto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen to accompliſh the ambitious ends</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Princes,</hi> vve have hazzarded our <hi>Friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To trouble, and infringe the <hi>Peace</hi> of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>VVho vvould not vvillingly have been our <hi>Foes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till many <hi>hundred thouſands</hi> are undone,</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie the <hi>boundleſs Luſt</hi> of <hi>One;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Squandring away thoſe <hi>Bleſſings</hi> to th'increaſe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Diſcord,</hi> which we might have kept in Peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How many a goodly <hi>City, Town</hi> and <hi>Field,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich did a comfortable Dwelling yeild</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116015:9"/>
                  <l>To <hi>Millions,</hi> who were no way intereſted</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Tyrants</hi> Quarrels, have of late been waſted?</l>
                  <l>And, what a ſad <hi>Accompt</hi> to make have they</l>
                  <l>Upon whoſe heads, that <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Spoil</hi> doth lie?</l>
                  <l>Believe it; though to keep from Violation</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> which have reſpect to every <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD's <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Juſtice,</hi> doth engage</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Nations</hi> on each other, War to wage;</l>
                  <l>Yet, uſe they ſhould not make of His <hi>Commiſſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie their <hi>Vengeance,</hi> their <hi>Ambitions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Avarice;</hi> nor any vvay extend them</l>
                  <l>Beyond thoſe Ends for which he doth intend them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is but little leſs then Blaſphemy</l>
                  <l>The Works of <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo to miſ-apply</l>
                  <l>As this <hi>Muſe</hi> doth, who in a <hi>Strain</hi> doth write,</l>
                  <l>As if none could expreſs a <hi>Glow-Worm's</hi> light</l>
                  <l>Unleſs he did Hyperbolize, ſo far,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, to equalize it to a <hi>Star.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He ſeems, as if he would inſinuate</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Nature,</hi> at his Death was paſſionate;</l>
                  <l>And makes that <hi>Creature</hi> ſpeak, which never <hi>Flatters</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Speaks</hi> at all, ſave onely in ſuch Matters,</l>
                  <l>As do concern GOD's glory, or, may ſhame</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Wits</hi> who groſsly miſ-apply the ſame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So,</hi> Nature, <hi>hath took Notice of His Death,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, ſighing, ſwel'd the Ocean with her breath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Death of her great</hi> Ruler <hi>to foreſhew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As 'twas preſaged when my <hi>Cat</hi> did <hi>Mew:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Nature,</hi> never heed in ſuch wiſe, took</l>
                  <l>Of any <hi>Princes</hi> Death, but, when it ſhook</l>
                  <l>The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> to ſee the SON OF GOD</l>
                  <l>Dead on the <hi>Croſs,</hi> with Arms diſplay'd abroad:</l>
                  <l>And from the <hi>Reverence</hi> that's due to ſuch!</l>
                  <l>High <hi>Myſteries,</hi> this, hath detracted much,</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116015:10"/>
                  <l>Of this kinde, and of ſuch-like <hi>Airy-Puffs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſuch deceivable, vain, empty ſtuffs,</l>
                  <l>Are moſt of all thoſe <hi>Books,</hi> and <hi>Trophies</hi> made,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Princes,</hi> to eternize them have had:</l>
                  <l>And, ſo ſmall credit, is attributed</l>
                  <l>To what is either to their <hi>Honour</hi> ſed,</l>
                  <l>Or their <hi>Diſhonour,</hi> that, <hi>wiſe Men</hi> reject it,</l>
                  <l>As of no Value; or at leaſt, ſuſpect it,</l>
                  <l>As an effect of <hi>Flatterie,</hi> or of <hi>Hate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though many ſet it at a higher Rate.</l>
                  <l>For, their <hi>Praiſe,</hi> whom we finde moſt prodigal</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>praiſes,</hi> merits no reſpect at all;</l>
                  <l>But, rather, from the <hi>Hearers,</hi> back returns</l>
                  <l>On him that's <hi>Prais'd,</hi> and on the <hi>Praiſer,</hi> Scornes:</l>
                  <l>And, ſeldom, ſhall you finde much <hi>worth</hi> in them,</l>
                  <l>That have <hi>immodest Praiſes,</hi> in eſteem.</l>
                  <l>Yet, theſe vain Blaſts of Fame, oft, ſound as loud</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Cannons,</hi> or as <hi>Thunder</hi> from a Cloud:</l>
                  <l>The People entertain them with <hi>Applauſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of much <hi>Expenſe,</hi> they are the needleſs Cauſe:</l>
                  <l>By theſe, <hi>wiſe Men,</hi> are otherwhile bewitch'd;</l>
                  <l>By theſe, are <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Flatterers</hi> inrich'd:</l>
                  <l>But, thereby, ſuch effects alone are got;</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Powder</hi> hath, when fired without <hi>ſhot.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, ſo to prize them, many men are given,</l>
                  <l>As if, without them, none could climb to Heaven;</l>
                  <l>Or, as if he, of whom moſt <hi>Lies</hi> we tell,</l>
                  <l>Should find leaſt Torments, in the Pains of Hell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Principle I own, is to adhere</l>
                  <l>To that <hi>Power,</hi> which <hi>Supremacy</hi> doth bear,</l>
                  <l>And I'll (without an Oath) be true to thoſe</l>
                  <l>VVho are by GOD, and by this <hi>People</hi> choſe,</l>
                  <l>Till they advance another, whom I ſee</l>
                  <l>Inveſted with <hi>Pow'r-Abſolute,</hi> to be;</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116015:10"/>
                  <l>And, whether he comes in, by <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Wrong,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leave that, to them, to whom it doth belong.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Him,</hi> I will ſerve, not with baſe <hi>Flatteries</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich blind his Judgement, or put out his eyes.</l>
                  <l>In my <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> I will never tell</l>
                  <l>To him, what I may fear he knowes too well:</l>
                  <l>Nor further then I know him, <hi>magnifie him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt his own <hi>conſcience</hi> knowing I <hi>belie him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or ſpeak more then my <hi>knowledge</hi> can acquire)</l>
                  <l>He, hereby know, I am a <hi>fawning Lyar.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Before him, I will thoſe things onely ſet,</l>
                  <l>VVhich I think, he may poſſibly forget,</l>
                  <l>Or, vvhich unto his knowledge are not brought,</l>
                  <l>Or (if known) not conſider'd as they ought;</l>
                  <l>And, do it ſo, that he ſhall not deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>VVhat's done, if he be either <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Wiſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If not, yet vvhen my <hi>Duty</hi> I have done,</l>
                  <l>I'll bear with Patience, vvhat enſues thereon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In all the <hi>Changes,</hi> vvhich have been of late,</l>
                  <l>I have preſerv'd this <hi>Rule</hi> inviolate.</l>
                  <l>Though ſome think not, vvhen one <hi>Pow'r</hi> vvas made two,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>wiſer Men,</hi> knew not vvhich vvay to go.</l>
                  <l>For, ſo far as my <hi>conſcience</hi> vvould permit,</l>
                  <l>I ſerv'd that <hi>Pow'r</hi> vvhich in the <hi>Throne</hi> did ſit</l>
                  <l>Moſt viſibly; in every <hi>change</hi> that came,</l>
                  <l>Siding vvith none in <hi>changing of the ſame:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And vvhen the <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> on him vvas plac'd</l>
                  <l>By GOD's permiſſion, vvho enjoy'd it laſt,</l>
                  <l>I did, accordingly, employ my Force</l>
                  <l>To keep vvhat might be <hi>naught,</hi> from being <hi>worſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Adventuring, ſometimes, ſo far therein,</l>
                  <l>That, to my diſadvantage, it hath bin.</l>
                  <l>I, was to him, in all things, alwayes true,</l>
                  <l>VVhich nothing took from his <hi>Superiors</hi> due.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116015:11"/>
                  <l>I did ſo far forth as it would conſiſt</l>
                  <l>VVith GOD's <hi>Praiſe,</hi> with the <hi>Publick Interest,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And his true <hi>Honour,</hi> do what in me lay</l>
                  <l>All thoſe <hi>Obſtructions</hi> to remove away,</l>
                  <l>VVhich, by diſabling him, might heretofore</l>
                  <l>Have made his <hi>Dangers,</hi> and our <hi>Miſchieves</hi> more.</l>
                  <l>And, though thoſe Services which I could do him</l>
                  <l>Some will deride, they have been uſeful to him:</l>
                  <l>For, 'tis at preſent, known, to more then <hi>One,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet living, (and was known to <hi>him that's gone</hi>)</l>
                  <l>That, in the greateſt hazzard he e'er had,</l>
                  <l>I, ſeaſ'nably, by <hi>Providence</hi> was made</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Inſtrument of Safety,</hi> when th' <hi>intention</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVas almoſt rip'ned, beyond all <hi>Prevention.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, to prevent them, vvho by his <hi>Diſgrace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Endeavour'd to deſtroy the <hi>publick Peace:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His <hi>Actings,</hi> too, I praiſed as I ought,</l>
                  <l>In what, I, them to be Praiſe-worthy thought,</l>
                  <l>Conſider'd in themſelves: But, his Deſart</l>
                  <l>Left in the <hi>main,</hi> to Him, who knew his Heart:</l>
                  <l>And knowing it to be GOD's priviledge,</l>
                  <l>(Even his alone) of <hi>Secret things</hi> to judge,</l>
                  <l>No further ever did, (nor ever will)</l>
                  <l>Of him, or any man, judge <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Since firſt this <hi>Principle</hi> to me was known,</l>
                  <l>And by Conſideration, made <hi>mine own.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is enough, that <hi>Princes</hi> whilſt they live</l>
                  <l>Are borne withal; and that vvhilſt they ſurvive</l>
                  <l>VVe hide their failings, that, none might through them</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pow'r,</hi> and that <hi>Authority</hi> contemn</l>
                  <l>By which they Govern: for, a <hi>Tyranny,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is ſomewhat better then an <hi>Anarchy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If, I ſuſpect my <hi>Prince</hi> a vvicked man,</l>
                  <l>To make him better, I'll do what I can;</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116015:11"/>
                  <l>Leſt, he that's next be worſe: As once by <hi>Paul</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Agrippa</hi> courted was, him court, I ſhall,</l>
                  <l>If, need be: or, vvill flatter him ſo far</l>
                  <l>As by our <hi>Servants,</hi> Children flatter'd are,</l>
                  <l>To make them do their Duties: but, not vvo hin.</l>
                  <l>For my own ends, to that which may undo him:</l>
                  <l>(VVhich I conceive, is ſuch a <hi>Pious fraud</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As GOD allows, and honeſt men applaud.)</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Life,</hi> I ſerv'd him thus; now <hi>Dead</hi> he lies</l>
                  <l>I'll ſpeak no more of him, then may ſuffice</l>
                  <l>To make thoſe better, and take better heed</l>
                  <l>VVho ſhall henceforward, in his Room ſucceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Examples, we from <hi>Holy-Writ,</hi> may take,</l>
                  <l>That of the <hi>Dead</hi> we nothing ought to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>But, vvhat is true; and that we are as well</l>
                  <l>Oblig'd, their <hi>failings</hi> as deſerts to tell.</l>
                  <l>That, GOD, may have due <hi>Praiſe</hi> by every one;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Men,</hi> by knowing truly, what is done,</l>
                  <l>In thoſe things, vvhich concern them; (and by whom</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Miſchieves,</hi> or their <hi>Benefits</hi> do come)</l>
                  <l>May actuate accordingly, in ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>The Dictates of their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and ſound <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It vvas not then thought (as now in theſe times</l>
                  <l>Perhaps, it may be) that, to blaze the crimes</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Eli, David,</hi> or <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> (though unto the <hi>State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of them had reſpect) vvas <hi>ſawcineſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or vvant of <hi>Manners,</hi> though they did expreſs</l>
                  <l>Both to thoſe <hi>times,</hi> and <hi>future Generations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Failings,</hi> vvith their proper <hi>aggravations.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And therefore, if a juſt occaſion be,</l>
                  <l>Expect the like <hi>plain-dealing</hi> novv from me:</l>
                  <l>For to the ſame <hi>End,</hi> I vvill do mine <hi>Arrants,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make good my <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> by their <hi>Warrants.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116015:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I, grant it <hi>Thankleſneſs,</hi> as he infers,</l>
                  <l>If we for <hi>Benefactors</hi> have no tears</l>
                  <l>When they are dead: For, I deſire we may</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Dues,</hi> both to the <hi>Dead</hi> and <hi>Living</hi> pay:</l>
                  <l>But, I conceive it more <hi>ingratitude,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Upon the World, our <hi>Fictions</hi> to obtrude,</l>
                  <l>And, let that as impertinent paſs by,</l>
                  <l>Which GOD <hi>permits,</hi> or <hi>acts,</hi> to glorify</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or his <hi>mercie,</hi> whoſe neglect;</l>
                  <l>Make other things, to want their due effects.</l>
                  <l>GOD, make us grateful for what is beſtown,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch wiſe, that to every one his own</l>
                  <l>We may aſcribe, and, not to any give</l>
                  <l>So much, that, of his dues, we him deprive;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſo much to one man, that, they may be</l>
                  <l>Defrauded, who, deſerv'd as well as He.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such <hi>Partialities,</hi> at firſt, brought in</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Tyrannies:</hi> By ſuch, <hi>Free-men</hi> have bin</l>
                  <l>Enſlaved by degrees, and thereunto</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Fawnings</hi> add more, then all elſe can do;</l>
                  <l>And 'tis impoſſible a means to finde</l>
                  <l>To keep thoſe <hi>Free,</hi> who have a <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> minde,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Curriſh nature;</hi> For, the firſt want <hi>courage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And give their <hi>Birth-rights,</hi> for a <hi>Miſs of Porrage:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The other, muſt like <hi>Bandogs</hi> chained be,</l>
                  <l>Elſe none who live among them, can be free.</l>
                  <l>GOD, grant us grace, ſo to bewail his <hi>Fate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who is deceaſt, as to rejoyce in that</l>
                  <l>Which is thereby <hi>deſign'd:</hi> and, to take heed</l>
                  <l>We do not complementally proceed</l>
                  <l>In <hi>formal mournings,</hi> till the <hi>Counterfeit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Makes us, thoſe <hi>Christian mournings</hi> to forget</l>
                  <l>Which are now cal'd for; and till we have more</l>
                  <l>True Cauſe of <hi>ſorrow</hi> then we had before;</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116015:12"/>
                  <l>And, for the <hi>Dead,</hi> purſue a <hi>formal grieving</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſtructive to the welfare of the <hi>Living:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt, when the <hi>Dead,</hi> their <hi>Dead,</hi> in earth ſhall cloth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One day,</hi> become a <hi>mourning-day</hi> to both.</l>
                  <l>For, to ſuſpect, juſt cauſe enough I find</l>
                  <l>Some miſchief, for <hi>that day</hi> would be <hi>deſign'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>acted</hi> too, if <hi>Vengeance</hi> could raiſe <hi>pow'r</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To do, what might be done at ſuch an hour:</l>
                  <l>As thoſe <hi>deſpights,</hi> do queſtionleſs aſſure</l>
                  <l>Which on his <hi>Scutcheon</hi> and his <hi>Portraiture</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVere lately acted, if believe we may</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſeems believ'd, and <hi>common Fame</hi> doth ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Interments of the Dead,</hi> were firſt intended</l>
                  <l>Leſt by them, they who <hi>live,</hi> might be offended</l>
                  <l>If not remov'd from ſight: Therefore, by giving</l>
                  <l>Things to the <hi>Dead,</hi> belonging to the <hi>living,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth injure both; and neither <hi>get,</hi> nor <hi>give</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such <hi>honour,</hi> as we may perhaps conceive:</l>
                  <l>But are occaſions rather of <hi>Diſgraces</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of returning durt into our Faces.</l>
                  <l>So Cynical my humor never was</l>
                  <l>To think, <hi>men</hi> ſhould be buried like an <hi>Aſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall I <hi>Judas-like,</hi> be diſcontent</l>
                  <l>To ſee a box of <hi>pretious Odors</hi> ſpent</l>
                  <l>In burying him; though for a while the <hi>Poor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May want it; if, their wants it make not more</l>
                  <l>Then they can bear; And, mends be made for that</l>
                  <l>Which they have ſuff'red ere it be too late.</l>
                  <l>But, I abhor it, when I do behold</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Walls</hi> clothed, and poor men expos'd to cold</l>
                  <l>And nakedneſs: or at their needleſs coſt</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>honour'd</hi> whilſt their <hi>credit's</hi> loſt</l>
                  <l>VVhich is more worth then <hi>Life;</hi> and which to ſave,</l>
                  <l>They many times, their <hi>Lives</hi> adventur'd have.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116015:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Small honour, by that <hi>Fun'rall-Pomp,</hi> is got</l>
                  <l>VVhere they who bear the charge approve it not.</l>
                  <l>To bring a <hi>Prince,</hi> with glory to his grave,</l>
                  <l>Is not to make his <hi>lifeleſs Image</hi> brave;</l>
                  <l>To give as great a reverence thereunto</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Pagans,</hi> to their <hi>Idols,</hi> us'd to do,</l>
                  <l>Or, as they, who like <hi>worſhip</hi> have appli'd</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>Image</hi> who was crucifi'd.</l>
                  <l>It is not to make <hi>Pageants</hi> at their coſt</l>
                  <l>(VVho think they have too much already loſt)</l>
                  <l>VVith thoſe vain <hi>Ceremonial Rites</hi> attended,</l>
                  <l>VVhereby, the <hi>ſober-minded</hi> are offended;</l>
                  <l>And till <hi>Spectators,</hi> Jeeringly do ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is a very coſtly Puppet-Play.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, till it gives them cauſe to be afear'd</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>way</hi> thereby, to worſe things is prepar'd:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>this way,</hi> was <hi>Idolatry</hi> brought in;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This way,</hi> moſt <hi>Superſtitions</hi> did begin;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>this way,</hi> if GOD let it be purſu'd</l>
                  <l>A little further, they will be renew'd</l>
                  <l>Till that day comes, in which, what men endeavor</l>
                  <l>To build up, ſhall deſtroyed be for ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Second (as 'tis ſayd)</l>
                  <l>Did, of a <hi>Funeral-Pageant,</hi> thus arayd,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Patern</hi> leave; which is reſembled much</l>
                  <l>By <hi>this;</hi> one <hi>circumſtance,</hi> (and ſome few ſuch)</l>
                  <l>Excepted, (and for ought that I yet know,</l>
                  <l>That might be privately, performed too.)</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Anti-roomes of State,</hi> with Blacks beclad,</l>
                  <l>Through which, men to th' <hi>Effigies</hi> paſſage had,</l>
                  <l>And, wherein they were forced to <hi>ſtand bare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Becauſe a <hi>property</hi> unuſeful there:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Pater-noſters,</hi> they ſhould there have ſed,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ave-Maries,</hi> for the <hi>Soul</hi> that's dead,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116015:13"/>
                  <l>If they that <hi>Ceremonie</hi> had obſerved</l>
                  <l>For which thoſe <hi>places</hi> were at firſt reſerved;</l>
                  <l>And, whereto (though unpractis'd at this day)</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Innovations,</hi> will perhaps make <hi>way.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVe are already, drawing very nigh</l>
                  <l>To <hi>ſuperſtitions,</hi> and <hi>Idolatrie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, at the <hi>Back-door,</hi> that is coming in,</l>
                  <l>VVhich at the <hi>Fore-door,</hi> hath expelled bin.</l>
                  <l>Who, would have thought, that <hi>we,</hi> who do neglect</l>
                  <l>One of the goodlieſt Piles of <hi>Architect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In all the <hi>Christian World,</hi> becauſe, long ſince,</l>
                  <l>It ſeem'd <hi>profan'd,</hi> by things which gave <hi>offence?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>we,</hi> ſhould raiſe up <hi>Trophies,</hi> in its ſtead,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Straws</hi> and <hi>Sticks,</hi> and <hi>Kexes</hi> to the Dead?</l>
                  <l>And with <hi>exploded Vanities,</hi> defile</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Palaces,</hi> and <hi>Temples</hi> of this <hi>Iſle?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, having ſeen what zeal expreſſed was</l>
                  <l>In pulling down of <hi>Croſſes, painted Glaſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Altars,</hi> Images of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And with theſe, of ſome <hi>inoffenſive things</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Did then ſuppoſe, he ſhould have liv'd to ſee</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Idol,</hi> in that place advanc'd to be,</l>
                  <l>Where heretofore, an <hi>Altar,</hi> and a <hi>Rood</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be adored by the <hi>People</hi> ſtood?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who can believe, that HE, who viliſide</l>
                  <l>Not long ago, the <hi>vanitie</hi> and <hi>pride</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of former <hi>Princes?</hi> That, HE, who had ſpoke</l>
                  <l>Againſt the <hi>heavie burthens,</hi> and the <hi>yoak</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By them impos'd, and was himſelf the <hi>Rod</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>ſword</hi> aſſum'd into the hand of GOD,</l>
                  <l>To root them out? That HE, who but of late,</l>
                  <l>VVhen he diſmiſt the <hi>Counſellors of State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sayd to their <hi>Sergeant,</hi> Take away that <hi>Bable;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(His <hi>Mace</hi> at that time, lying on the Table)</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116015:14"/>
                  <l>Should ever of his own accord, think fit</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Trinkets</hi> which he ſleighted to admit?</l>
                  <l>And, when he down into the <hi>Grave</hi> deſcended,</l>
                  <l>Should thither, with more <hi>vain pomps</hi> be attended</l>
                  <l>Then any <hi>Engliſh Prince,</hi> that heretofore</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Soveraign Scepter,</hi> in theſe <hi>Iſlands</hi> bore?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh! times, oh manners!</hi> how exceeding vain</l>
                  <l>Is mans <hi>Heart,</hi> and how giddy, is his <hi>Brain?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who thinketh not, that ſuch a <hi>Change</hi> hath ſeen,</l>
                  <l>And, heeds what they <hi>ſeem'd</hi> who ſo chang'd have been?</l>
                  <l>But, that, far <hi>greater Changes,</hi> will appear,</l>
                  <l>If GOD, prevents not, that which we may fear?</l>
                  <l>For that old <hi>Leven,</hi> which aſide was lay'd,</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>lump,</hi> is ſecretly convey'd:</l>
                  <l>And now <hi>corruptions,</hi> do ſo over-ſpread</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Body Politick,</hi> from foot to head,</l>
                  <l>That ſwarms of <hi>Hornets,</hi> and of <hi>Butterflies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Produc'd and fed, by new-ſprung Vanities,</l>
                  <l>Are like to multiply, till they ſhall drive</l>
                  <l>The <hi>lab'ring Bees,</hi> quite out of every <hi>Hive.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Excuſe my <hi>zeal,</hi> if over-tarr I'ſeem</l>
                  <l>In this point; For, from no diſguſt of <hi>him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For whoſe pretended honour this is done,</l>
                  <l>Nor from <hi>malevolence</hi> to any one</l>
                  <l>Who did deſign it, this <hi>expreſſion</hi> flows;</l>
                  <l>Nor from what <hi>Prejudice,</hi> may miſ-ſuppoſe;</l>
                  <l>But, from the <hi>Cauſe</hi> that's given of <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, what I fear may be the <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What <hi>Meteors, Windes,</hi> and <hi>Tempeſts</hi> do foreſhow</l>
                  <l>I know not, neither take much care to know;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, they rather warn us, to take heed</l>
                  <l>What's <hi>doing,</hi> then declare what will <hi>ſucceed:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, by our <hi>Flatteries,</hi> and by other things</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Pride</hi> produces; by what daily ſprings,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116015:14"/>
                  <l>From our <hi>ſelf-ſeekings;</hi> from our <hi>Avarices,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, from our many other ſordid <hi>Vices,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This, I am ſure's <hi>preſag'd,</hi> that if we run</l>
                  <l>Much farther, in the <hi>Courſe</hi> that's yet hel'd on,</l>
                  <l>(And, GOD, our folly to take place permits)</l>
                  <l>We ſhall ere long run quite out of our <hi>wits;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, be at laſt deſtroyed all together,</l>
                  <l>By that <hi>Storm,</hi> which I ſee approaching hither.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, who am I, that ſay I do foreſee</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Storm,</hi> that you ſhould credit give to me?</l>
                  <l>How can ſuch things, to me, you ſay be known?</l>
                  <l>How know you, when the <hi>Sun</hi> is almoſt down</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>Night</hi> will follow? and the <hi>Day</hi> draw near</l>
                  <l>When you behold the <hi>morning-Star</hi> appear?</l>
                  <l>Look not on him, who tells what may enſue,</l>
                  <l>But look to that, whereby you may eſchew</l>
                  <l>The threatned <hi>Plague,</hi> which (as GOD's threatnings all</l>
                  <l>Are for the moſt part) is <hi>conditional.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To that intent, your <hi>old neglected Friend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Amongſt you, <hi>one Remembrance more,</hi> will ſend</l>
                  <l>To ſecond <hi>this,</hi> before perceive he ſhall</l>
                  <l>A <hi>MENE TEKEL,</hi> written on your Wall,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs he ſees GOD's patience out of date,</l>
                  <l>And all <hi>fore-warnings,</hi> like to come too late.</l>
                  <l>Mean while, take this that follows: For he knows</l>
                  <l>You look for <hi>Signs,</hi> of that which he <hi>fore-ſhows;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, theſe (although they trivial may appear)</l>
                  <l>Are true <hi>Fore-tokens</hi> of what's drawing near.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Black Clouds,</hi> are now aſcending o're theſe <hi>Lands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Figures</hi> do portend ſome <hi>humane hands</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Promoting that great <hi>Storm;</hi> But, when abroad</l>
                  <l>It <hi>ſpreads,</hi> you will perceive the hand of GOD,</l>
                  <l>Who, by a <hi>ſlow-approaching</hi> doth expreſs,</l>
                  <l>He comes to puniſh, with unwillingneſs.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116015:15"/>
                  <l>Each man, who is not wilful, plainly ſees,</l>
                  <l>He etners into <hi>Judgement,</hi> by degrees,</l>
                  <l>To move us to <hi>Repentance,</hi> that the <hi>Doom,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But threatned yet, might vaniſh ere it come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOD, hath made known unto us, in ſome meaſure,</l>
                  <l>By every <hi>Element,</hi> his juſt Diſpleaſure:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, without which, nothing is enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>Have all our late <hi>Enjoyments</hi> much deſtroy'd.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>ſudden Fires,</hi> our dwellings are conſum'd,</l>
                  <l>And, into ſmoak, our <hi>pretious things</hi> are fum'd.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Waters,</hi> in their Wombs, have ſwallow'd up</l>
                  <l>No little <hi>Portion</hi> of the <hi>Merchants</hi> hope,</l>
                  <l>And, overflowing <hi>new, and Antient Bounds,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Swept Flocks and Herds out of the lower Grounds.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Air,</hi> by <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Blaſtings, Froſts</hi> and <hi>Snows,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſtroy'd our <hi>laſt Crops,</hi> in their faireſt ſhows;</l>
                  <l>Yea, after publickly we made Confeſſions</l>
                  <l>That, GOD, accepting our <hi>Humiliations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had thereupon, vouchſafed pregnant Hopes</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Future Health,</hi> and of more <hi>Plenteous Crops;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Even ſince that <hi>likely hope,</hi> we, for our <hi>Sin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Depriv'd of that <hi>Expectancy</hi> have bin.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Earth</hi> which bears us, too; for our <hi>Offences</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With-holds her <hi>Bounty.</hi> Their ſweet <hi>Influences</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Heavens</hi> withdraw. <hi>Death,</hi> when unlook'd for, ſeizes</l>
                  <l>More oft then formerly, by <hi>New-Diſeaſes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, they, to give <hi>Accompt,</hi> are call'[d upon,</l>
                  <l>Who liv'd, as if accomptable to none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hereto, the <hi>Naturaliſt,</hi> perhaps will ſay,</l>
                  <l>Such things do happen to us every day,</l>
                  <l>Or, in a ſhort time, either more or leſs:</l>
                  <l>Which I will grant; but notwithſtanding, this</l>
                  <l>He muſt grant too, that from the <hi>Worlds beginning</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe vvere, and are, the known <hi>Rewards of Sinning:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:116015:15"/>
                  <l>That they are alſo <hi>Signes,</hi> GOD vvill bring greater</l>
                  <l>And more <hi>Afflictions,</hi> if we grow not better:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Judgements,</hi> (though they be not general)</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Families,</hi> and <hi>Private Perſons</hi> fall</l>
                  <l>Ev'n day by day: That, we have lately ſeen</l>
                  <l>Large <hi>Vials of GOD's Wrath,</hi> powr'd forth have been</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſtubborn <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and the <hi>Scot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To warn us what will alſo be our <hi>Lot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that none ſhould GOD's Patience, therefore ſlight,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe a long time, He forbears to ſmite;</l>
                  <l>Or, puff'd by <hi>timely Warnings,</hi> when he ſends them,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe this way, to us he recommends them:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>this way,</hi> they declared were of old,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>this way,</hi> they ſhall now again be told.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, hear me further, and relate I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Some things, which do not ev'ry year befall;</l>
                  <l>Our ableſt <hi>Horſe,</hi> (ev'n thoſe perhaps, wherein</l>
                  <l>More <hi>truſt</hi> repoſed was, then ſhould have bin)</l>
                  <l>Die ſuddenly, and Ditches are beſtrow'd</l>
                  <l>With thoſe <hi>Eones,</hi> whereupon our <hi>Gallants</hi> rode:</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Stink</hi> (as once a <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaid) aſcends,</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſtill, his hand againſt us, GOD, extends.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Leggs,</hi> likewiſe, which are our <hi>Second-Strength</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do reel already, and will ſink at length</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Body</hi> which they bear: the <hi>Wings</hi> by which</l>
                  <l>We flew from Shoar to Shoar, and were made rich,</l>
                  <l>Begin to flag, and fly not to and fro,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch Succeſs, as they were wont to do.</l>
                  <l>Some, whoſe <hi>new Honours</hi> bloomed but <hi>laſt Spring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fell with the Leaf,</hi> to ſhew, how vain a thing</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ambition</hi> is, and let them underſtand</l>
                  <l>VVho flouriſh yet, their <hi>Winter</hi> is at hand.</l>
                  <l>Much, of our pretious <hi>Life-Blood</hi> up is drunk,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Sinews</hi> of our <hi>Pow'r</hi> are crack'd and ſhrunk;</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116015:16"/>
                  <l>Our <hi>Honour,</hi> vvith our <hi>Publick Faith</hi> is loſt;</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Private Credits</hi> are deſtroy'd almoſt:</l>
                  <l>And, hard it is to ſay, whether the <hi>Debtor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Creditor,</hi> is in Condition better.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Parliaments</hi> Securities are ſlighted,</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>He,</hi> whom they have by their <hi>Acts</hi> invited</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe, (and, of paying whoſe juſt Dues</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> made fair ſhews)</l>
                  <l>Though, more then <hi>ten years,</hi> are elapſed ſince,</l>
                  <l>Gets neither <hi>Mony, Land,</hi> nor <hi>Recompence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor hope of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> but, <hi>Suits,</hi> to the waſting</l>
                  <l>Of his Eſtate, which may be everlaſting:</l>
                  <l>And, they, who ſhould, from theſe <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> clear him,</l>
                  <l>Either regard him not, or, or ſit and jeer him;</l>
                  <l>Though both by <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> they ſtand oblig'd</l>
                  <l>To ſee the <hi>Publick Credit</hi> diſ-engag'd.</l>
                  <l>That which is due to <hi>Poor Men,</hi> is delay'd</l>
                  <l>Till they have loſt it <hi>twice,</hi> ere 'tis <hi>once</hi> pay'd.</l>
                  <l>He that hath <hi>Lent,</hi> till he can <hi>lend no more,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is ſure to loſe all, that he lent before;</l>
                  <l>And, that which to be <hi>given,</hi> hath been thought,</l>
                  <l>Proves dearer otherwhile, then vvhat we <hi>bought.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All which things, being rightly underſtood,</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Signes</hi> (if not of <hi>much ill</hi>) of <hi>ſmall good.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Should I here mention all <hi>Prevarications,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which being <hi>fifteen Years together,</hi> tide</l>
                  <l>(As by the Leg) near <hi>London</hi> to reſide,</l>
                  <l>They vvould fill up a <hi>Volume:</hi> and, but that</l>
                  <l>Thouſands can vvitneſs vvhat I might relate,</l>
                  <l>It vvould be thought, I did <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruths</hi> aver,</l>
                  <l>And, that, I vvere a ſhameleſs ſlanderer:</l>
                  <l>For, our <hi>Abominations</hi> have exceeded</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and are more then can be heeded.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116015:16"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>It can by no true <hi>Engliſhman</hi> be born,</l>
                  <l>Without much <hi>Indignation,</hi> and more <hi>ſeorn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſee <hi>Foot-walkers,</hi> vvhen on <hi>Horſe-back</hi> ſet,</l>
                  <l>So much their late Condition to forget,</l>
                  <l>As, ſuperciliouſly to look on thoſe</l>
                  <l>By whom, out of <hi>Obſcurity</hi> they roſe;</l>
                  <l>And when men ſeek but <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and their <hi>own,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How theſe, (as if to have an Alms beſtown</l>
                  <l>They vvere implor'd) provoke vvith harſh replies</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſuff'ring-Suppliant,</hi> till his <hi>Blood</hi> doth riſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Words</hi> are ſpoken, vvhereon doth enſue</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>Wrong,</hi> becauſe he ſpoke vvhat's <hi>true.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sometimes, from vveek to vveek, from year to year,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Suits</hi> are defer'd, vvhich they vvith ſpeed ſhould hear;</l>
                  <l>Yet, nothing then effected, but expence,</l>
                  <l>More adding to a former indigence.</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> vvhich fully might enable</l>
                  <l>To do their <hi>Work;</hi> they ſpend in <hi>Bibble-babble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or needleſs <hi>Complements;</hi> and vvill not vvave</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Feaſt</hi> or <hi>Viſit,</hi> though it vvere to ſave</l>
                  <l>A man from Ruine; and when <hi>Plaints are long,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>long Oppreſſion,</hi> they away are flung.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Suppliants</hi> are forc'd to hunt them thorough</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſtarting holes,</hi> like <hi>Rabbets</hi> through their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</l>
                  <l>Yet, hardly come to ſpeak with them, before</l>
                  <l>They (as it were) ſet <hi>Purſe-Nets,</hi> at each door;</l>
                  <l>And then, unleſs they likewiſe, get a <hi>Hay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pitch'd round about them, they will ſlip away.</l>
                  <l>That, which is abſolutely in their Pow'r,</l>
                  <l>And, might be finiſhed in half an hour,</l>
                  <l>Is made a <hi>Buſineſs</hi> during term of life;</l>
                  <l>And, then, the <hi>Suitor</hi> dies without relief:</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Suppliants</hi> are oft defer'd ſo long,</l>
                  <l>That, they at laſt, vvho ſhould redreſs the Wrong</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116015:17"/>
                  <l>Are puzzel'd too; and ſuch as have been griev'd</l>
                  <l>So num'rous grow, that few can be reliev'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No marvail;</hi> for the <hi>Body-Politick</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In every part almoſt, is <hi>Lame</hi> or <hi>Sick;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So, that, thoſe Limbs, which in themſelves are able,</l>
                  <l>Are render'd by the reſt unſerviceable;</l>
                  <l>For, though the <hi>Foot</hi> be whole, it cannot go</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, the <hi>Great Gout,</hi> lames the <hi>greateſt Toe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, very mean performances are found</l>
                  <l>Where, in <hi>both Hands,</hi> there's but <hi>one finger</hi> ſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, it objected be, that ſuch <hi>Delayes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May juſtly be occaſion'd many vvwayes;</l>
                  <l>'Tis granted, that, it may be ſo in ſome;</l>
                  <l>But not till <hi>twice ſeven years</hi> elaps'd become,</l>
                  <l>Without apparent wrong: And, that abuſes</l>
                  <l>Are this way offer'd, for which no excuſes</l>
                  <l>May be allow'd, ſome thouſands living are,</l>
                  <l>VVho, if need be, thereof can vvitneſs bear.</l>
                  <l>VVhen <hi>Publick-Debts</hi> have many yeers been due,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Creditors</hi> compel'd for them to ſue</l>
                  <l>Till they, in <hi>Labour, time,</hi> and other <hi>Coſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Principal,</hi> and ſo much more have loſt,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Shameleſs Officers</hi> inſtead of paying,</l>
                  <l>Put off the <hi>Creditors,</hi> with this harſh ſaying,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis an old Debt;</hi> as if men did them wrong</l>
                  <l>To ask for that vvhich had been due ſo long;</l>
                  <l>And, that, the way to right them, vvho implore</l>
                  <l>Redreſs for <hi>old wrongs,</hi> vvere to do them more.</l>
                  <l>Nay, there is ſo much falſehood and deceit</l>
                  <l>In many, that, they make poor men to vvait</l>
                  <l>From day to day, from morning untill noon,</l>
                  <l>From noon till night, <hi>Delay,</hi> ſtill ſpinning on,</l>
                  <l>(Till many dayes and nights, and weeks are ſpent)</l>
                  <l>As if to grant their <hi>Suits</hi> they truly meant,</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116015:17"/>
                  <l>Although they from the firſt hour, did intend</l>
                  <l>To give them flat denial in the end.</l>
                  <l>And, uſually, when they ſpeak fair and ſmile,</l>
                  <l>They pick your Purſe, or cut your Throat the while.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They, who are guilty of ſuch things, and know</l>
                  <l>That I, and thouſands, know them to be ſo,</l>
                  <l>Will ſay, perhaps, I <hi>Rail;</hi> but 'tis no matter;</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Rail,</hi> is ſomewhat better then to <hi>Flatter.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>None but a <hi>Fool</hi> with term it <hi>Railing,</hi> when</l>
                  <l>Reproaching <hi>Vices,</hi> we conceal the <hi>Men.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>None, but a <hi>Brazen-fac'd-Offender</hi> dares,</l>
                  <l>Exceptions take to that, which truth avers;</l>
                  <l>And none but <hi>Mad-men</hi> caſt reproach on thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who chide them, to prevent their overthows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I will proceed to further Demonſtration</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe <hi>Signes,</hi> which portend a <hi>Deſolation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strange Prodigies,</hi> which not ſo oft have been</l>
                  <l>In this our <hi>Clymate,</hi> are now often ſeen.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Looks,</hi> or <hi>Language,</hi> it is hard to know</l>
                  <l>VVhom you may now repute your Friend or Foe:</l>
                  <l>They, who have but <hi>one Head,</hi> have now <hi>two Faces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>two Tongues:</hi> Both their <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Places,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Members of the ſelf-ſame Body ſhift;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though neither of them, hath the others gift.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Little Toe,</hi> although to be a <hi>Thumb</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It hath been rais'd, will not content become,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs it may obtain that <hi>both the Hands</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall be ſubjected under his commands.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Head's cut off;</hi> and though that in its ſtead,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Foot,</hi> may have admittance to be <hi>Head,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It (quite forgetting what it vvas before)</l>
                  <l>VVill ſcarce be pleas'd, unleſs it may be more.</l>
                  <l>Nay, from <hi>Ambition, Vermine</hi> are not free;</l>
                  <l>That naſty <hi>Body-Lice,</hi> would <hi>Head-Lice</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:116015:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe wicked <hi>Spirits</hi> that engender ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Among us, more then ever, are now rife.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stupidity, Diſtraction, Giddineſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith ſuch-like, many thouſands do poſſeſs;</l>
                  <l>And, haunted now, our <hi>Habitations</hi> are</l>
                  <l>VVith vvorſe <hi>Hobgoblins,</hi> then the <hi>Faires</hi> vvere.</l>
                  <l>To their own <hi>Principles,</hi> but very few,</l>
                  <l>Save <hi>Enemies</hi> and <hi>wicked Men</hi> are true.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Changes,</hi> which but rarely did befal,</l>
                  <l>Are in theſe Iſlands Epidemical.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Servant</hi> rides, the <hi>Maſter</hi> goes on foot,</l>
                  <l>And, is his <hi>Servant</hi>'s Servant, too, to boot:</l>
                  <l>The ſilly <hi>School-Boyes</hi> do preſume to teach;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Foxes</hi> pray, the fooliſh <hi>Geeſe</hi> do preach;</l>
                  <l>And, moſt things are ſo turned <hi>topſy-turvy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That what looks beſt, methinks, is very ſcurvy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not onely thoſe <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> among whom</l>
                  <l>We live, oppreſſors of us are become,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Brethren</hi> alſo ſtrive; yea, <hi>Saints,</hi> with ire</l>
                  <l>Are ſo inflam'd, that they can out for fire</l>
                  <l>From Heaven, on thoſe, who onely diſagree</l>
                  <l>From them, in things that but indiff'rent be;</l>
                  <l>And, we are told, by one whom I believe,</l>
                  <l>VVhat it portends, where ſuch things we perceive</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Natural Experience,</hi> we have found</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>Inſtruments</hi> which yeild a diff'ring ſound,</l>
                  <l>(And <hi>Tones,</hi> are <hi>Voices,</hi> though they various be)</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Conſort,</hi> do melodiouſly agree.</l>
                  <l>So, we ſhould likewiſe, finde theſe <hi>Differences</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Judgement,</hi> whereat we now take Offences,</l>
                  <l>VVould make true <hi>Harmony,</hi> if we to Him</l>
                  <l>Did leave it, who knows how to order them;</l>
                  <l>And took more care (then moſt of us have done)</l>
                  <l>To ſet our own <hi>Tongues,</hi> and our <hi>Hearts</hi> in tune.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:116015:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>Friends</hi> in Forraign Parts, and here at home,</l>
                  <l>Each of the other jealous are become;</l>
                  <l>And ſhould there be a <hi>Breach,</hi> no Mortal knows</l>
                  <l>VVhether our <hi>old Friends,</hi> or our <hi>elder Foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVould prove our greateſt <hi>Enemies;</hi> or, whether</l>
                  <l>They, would to miſchieve us, joyn all together.</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>New Allies,</hi> are likely at our need,</l>
                  <l>To be to us, but an <hi>Aegyptian Reed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, like a coſtly <hi>Armour,</hi> by whoſe weight,</l>
                  <l>VVe are more tir'd, then guarded in the Fight;</l>
                  <l>And ſomewhat ſounds from them (unleſs Fame lies)</l>
                  <l>VVhich an <hi>unpleaſing Sequel</hi> ſignifies.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things, (at leaſt united) do foreſhew</l>
                  <l>That, ſome <hi>foul Weather</hi> ſhortly may enſue:</l>
                  <l>GOD, alſo ſtands, with Arm outſtretched ſtill,</l>
                  <l>The Sentence of His <hi>Juſtice</hi> to fulfil.</l>
                  <l>If we conſult but with meer <hi>Human Reaſon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhat's likely to ſucceed at ſuch a Seaſon</l>
                  <l>As this appears, by loſs of him alone,</l>
                  <l>VVho lately was removed from the Throne:</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Counſels</hi> and what <hi>Coſt</hi> it will require</l>
                  <l>To keep ſo many <hi>Irons in the Fire</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he hath left <hi>unwrought;</hi> and what it would</l>
                  <l>Coſt more, to let them lie till they are cold.</l>
                  <l>If vve conſider, That he was of late</l>
                  <l>The Middle, and, main <hi>Pillar,</hi> of this <hi>State;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Atlas</hi> (as the Attribute that's giv'n</l>
                  <l>By one, hath term'd Him) of our <hi>Britiſh Heav'n,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, into what <hi>Confuſions,</hi> it is thought</l>
                  <l>All things at his Deceaſe, might have been brought;</l>
                  <l>Obſerving therewithal (without concluding</l>
                  <l>Upon falſe <hi>Theſes,</hi> or, our ſelves deluding)</l>
                  <l>In what apparent Dangers we are left,</l>
                  <l>By being, at this time, of him bereft,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116015:19"/>
                  <l>It may portend, although the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhines yet,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Storm</hi> will riſe before that he doth ſet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet, we ought not ſo much to reflect</l>
                  <l>Our thoughts on Him, that we thoſe things neglect</l>
                  <l>Which more concern us; or ſuppoſe that we</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd of any ſuch advantage be,</l>
                  <l>As is conceived; for, he had not gone,</l>
                  <l>But, that, the work ordain'd for him vvas done.</l>
                  <l>GOD, rais'd him, by <hi>Destroying,</hi> to prepare</l>
                  <l>A vvay for that which he intends to rear,</l>
                  <l>And, to that purpoſe qualifi'd him ſo,</l>
                  <l>As they were, vvhom of old he call'd to do</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Services;</hi> and, as it ſeems, intended</l>
                  <l>No further uſe of him, when that vvas ended:</l>
                  <l>He ſaw, the <hi>Pow'r</hi> vvhich vvas on him beſtowne</l>
                  <l>Imployed in <hi>Deſignments</hi> of his own;</l>
                  <l>Then, re-aſſum'd it: and, they had been troubled</l>
                  <l>Perhaps, who pray his <hi>Spirit</hi> might be doubled</l>
                  <l>On his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> if GOD, ſhould have ſaid</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>AMEN,</hi> to that, for which they blindly pray'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVe, likewiſe, (as of late that <hi>Parliament</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From vvhom he took the <hi>Supreme Government</hi>)</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Idolized,</hi> that, vve thought too little</l>
                  <l>Confer'd upon him by the <hi>Soveraign Title</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich, GOD permitted him to undertake.</l>
                  <l>And, what his <hi>Army</hi> pleas'd of him to make.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>govern us,</hi> vve long'd for ſuch a <hi>Thing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As other Nations have; forſooth, a <hi>King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith all the former burthenſome <hi>Aray</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> which vvas lately took away:</l>
                  <l>Though he, as much as <hi>Fleſh and Blood</hi> could do,</l>
                  <l>Refus'd it, vvith ſome perſeverance too.</l>
                  <l>And, not content to make him parallel</l>
                  <l>VVith all who are recorded to excel</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:116015:19"/>
                  <l>In <hi>Vertues,</hi> by <hi>Prophane</hi> or <hi>Sacred Story;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But plac'd him, in a higher <hi>Sphere</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVe gave him Attributes, vvhich unto none</l>
                  <l>Belongs, but to the <hi>Deitie</hi> alone;</l>
                  <l>And towards him, our ſelves oft ſo behaved,</l>
                  <l>As if by him alone, we could be ſaved;</l>
                  <l>VVhich peradventure, did provoke GOD's vvrath</l>
                  <l>To do to Him and Us, as done He hath.</l>
                  <l>GOD's dealing therefore, let us duly vveigh,</l>
                  <l>To do him all the honour, that we may:</l>
                  <l>For no <hi>reſpect of Perſons, Love,</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should from that <hi>Duty, flatter</hi> or <hi>deter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To that intent, it will have ſome Relation,</l>
                  <l>To know and heed, that his <hi>laſt Viſitation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> did that <hi>Day</hi> on him appear,</l>
                  <l>VVhich made the time compleatly juſt a Year,</l>
                  <l>Since he ſolemnized a <hi>Publick Faſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To pacifie GOD's <hi>Wrath</hi> for <hi>Failings Paſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As alſo for removing from our <hi>Clime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Sickneſſes,</hi> as raged at that time:</l>
                  <l>And, that, ſome <hi>Cautions,</hi> for that day prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>VVere in their Seaſon, unto him prefer'd,</l>
                  <l>To minde him vvhat ſmall good could be expected</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Formal-Faſts,</hi> vvhere <hi>Juſtice</hi> was neglected;</l>
                  <l>And what at laſt would follow thereupon,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Works of Mercy,</hi> were ſtill left undone.</l>
                  <l>At that time, ſuch <hi>Pre-Cautions</hi> tendred vvere</l>
                  <l>(As, if need be, hereafter you ſhall hear)</l>
                  <l>For, GOD, to offer them, did me incline,</l>
                  <l>And, to his hands, they were prefer'd by mine:</l>
                  <l>But, whether he peruſed them or no,</l>
                  <l>Since they preſented were, I neither know,</l>
                  <l>Nor vvhat <hi>Effect</hi> they had, if that be none,</l>
                  <l>VVhich at the years end, did enſue thereon.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116015:20"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>We ſhould conſider too, how on <hi>that day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Juſt that day <hi>twelve-month</hi> he was took away,</l>
                  <l>(Wherein he kept a <hi>Formal Celebration</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Thankfulneſs,</hi> for publike preſervation)</l>
                  <l>That <hi>very day,</hi> of his chief <hi>Triumphs</hi> turning</l>
                  <l>Into a ſad and <hi>Fatal day of mourning:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How <hi>that day,</hi> whereon (if <hi>Fame</hi> hath not lide)</l>
                  <l>He purpos'd to be crowned <hi>King,</hi> he dide;</l>
                  <l>Leaving an <hi>Image,</hi> with a waxen Face,</l>
                  <l>To be inſtal'd, and crowned in his place:</l>
                  <l>Which, as ſince we defac'd <hi>Crowns,</hi> 'twas the <hi>firſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That wore one, I deſire, may be the <hi>worſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ſhall from this time forward, live to bear</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Soveraign Scepter,</hi> or a Crown to wear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If we conſider duly as we ought,</l>
                  <l>Theſe things; with ſuch like, as to ſerious thought</l>
                  <l>Are thereby tendred; more, from thence there might</l>
                  <l>Inferred be, then I think fit to write.</l>
                  <l>Or, ſhould I tell, vvhat vvas prepar'd, likewiſe,</l>
                  <l>To make compleat his <hi>Formal Sacrifize</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Laſt mentioned, and what effects it had,</l>
                  <l>Some wholſome uſes, might thereof be made</l>
                  <l>Which muſt deferred be; becauſe my <hi>Reaſon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perſwades me, that they are not, yet in <hi>ſeaſon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know a <hi>Flatt'rer,</hi> feared not to ſay</l>
                  <l>That, was the <hi>third time,</hi> his <hi>Victorious day</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By conqu'ring <hi>Death:</hi> But, <hi>wiſemen,</hi> do contemn</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Gloſs,</hi> becauſe, that day, <hi>Death conquer'd him;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, do believe, and know, that none but <hi>he</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who dide for our <hi>Redemption</hi> on a <hi>Tree</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And, rais'd himſelf, to breathe immortal breath)</l>
                  <l>Ought to be ſtil'd the <hi>Conqueror of Death.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He onely, vvho, above the Heav'ns doth dwell,</l>
                  <l>And conquered vvith <hi>Death,</hi> both <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116015:20"/>
                  <l>Deſerves that <hi>Attribute:</hi> and they, vvho dare,</l>
                  <l>To others give the ſame, <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> are,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Except in that ſenſe,</hi> which, makes all who die</l>
                  <l>In him, partakers of his <hi>Victorie.</hi>)</l>
                  <l>He had his ſhare of <hi>Honour,</hi> and, not little</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Portion</hi> was; Let not his <hi>Masters</hi> Title</l>
                  <l>Aſcribed be to him: For, they, who hear it,</l>
                  <l>And are his <hi>Servants,</hi> cannot, will not bear it;</l>
                  <l>Nor be affraid to ſpeak, vvhat may encreaſe</l>
                  <l>GOD's honour, vvhoſe ſoe're it maketh leſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOD call'd him hence <hi>that day,</hi> to make us heed,</l>
                  <l>That, he in all his <hi>Actings</hi> doth proceed</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure;</hi> both to <hi>places,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Times</hi> referring them in many caſes,</l>
                  <l>To make obſervable his <hi>Viſitations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As alſo, to raiſe up our contemplations</l>
                  <l>To that, vvhich he <hi>Deſigns:</hi> yea, he advances</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>executions,</hi> oft, with <hi>Circumſtances,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not common; that, by fearching, we may finde</l>
                  <l>His <hi>meaning,</hi> and conform unto his <hi>minde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know, he vvas upon <hi>that day,</hi> advis'd</l>
                  <l>To ſomewhat, vvhich he ſhould not have deſpis'd</l>
                  <l>Whereto he gave ſmall heed, or none at all,</l>
                  <l>Till vvhat vvas juſtly feared did befal:</l>
                  <l>And, vvho knows, vvhat beſide that vvwas neglected?</l>
                  <l>VVhat vvas pretended then, vvhat, ſince projected?</l>
                  <l>Or, vvhat <hi>miſe-proſecuted,</hi> or <hi>miſ-done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which might provoke the great <hi>Almighty-one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To call him on that very day from hence,</l>
                  <l>VVhich vvas the day of his <hi>magnificence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And lay the <hi>Scepter</hi> level with <hi>the ſpade.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh! make thereof, ſuch uſe as ſhould be made;</l>
                  <l>For, knowing vvhat I know, relates thereto,</l>
                  <l>I, cannot unobſerved let it go.</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116015:21"/>
                  <l>We know that <hi>Death,</hi> vvhich is the hire of <hi>Sin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On that day, always payable hath bin,</l>
                  <l>In vvhich 'tis acted, though, GOD, by reprieve</l>
                  <l>Defers it oft, or, vvholly doth forgive.</l>
                  <l>We know there are ſome ſins, for vvhich, ev'n they</l>
                  <l>VVho are GOD'S <hi>choſen ones,</hi> are took away</l>
                  <l>From thoſe <hi>Enjoyments,</hi> vvhich they might have had,</l>
                  <l>Until a Forfeiture of them is made.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes,</hi> for ſpeaking raſhly, was denyed</l>
                  <l>The <hi>promis'd Land,</hi> and in that <hi>Deſart</hi> dyed,</l>
                  <l>Where others fell; and, thus, it doth befal</l>
                  <l>To many of GOD's <hi>Saints,</hi> if not to all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We either know, or vve ſhould know, likewiſe,</l>
                  <l>That, for our <hi>National impieties</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As vvell as for their own <hi>ſins,</hi> Princes may</l>
                  <l>In <hi>wrath</hi> be <hi>given,</hi> or, be <hi>took away.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Holy-Ghoſt</hi> hath ſaid, that, <hi>when to lies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>King gives ear</hi> (and ſuch are <hi>Flatteries</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The people, there are wicked.</hi> And, our ſin</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Cauſe in chief,</hi> hath peradventure bin,</l>
                  <l>VVhich, from his firſt <hi>Intentions,</hi> him declin'd,</l>
                  <l>To that vvhich vvas not for our <hi>weal</hi> deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor for his <hi>honour:</hi> yea, <hi>our ſelves</hi> vve may</l>
                  <l>Moſt juſtly blame, if he forſook the way</l>
                  <l>VVherein, he by the <hi>Publike-Card</hi> ſhould ſteer:</l>
                  <l>For, ſome of us thereto his <hi>Tempters</hi> were,</l>
                  <l>And, by our <hi>ſervile Flatt'ries,</hi> both made voyd</l>
                  <l>His firſt <hi>Reſolves,</hi> and our <hi>own Hopes</hi> deſtroy'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As, therefore, when GOD, gave the <hi>Jews a King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He then, did by a dreadful <hi>Thundering,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by a <hi>great Rain</hi> in their Harveſt time,</l>
                  <l>Declare that they had much diſpleaſed him;</l>
                  <l>So, peradventure, that <hi>Storm,</hi> which did roar</l>
                  <l>So univerſally four days before</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116015:21"/>
                  <l>He took hence our <hi>Protector,</hi> was intended</l>
                  <l>To ſignifie, that he is much offended</l>
                  <l>With all this <hi>Land,</hi> ev'n from him that's on high</l>
                  <l>Enthron'd, to him, who in the ſtreet doth lie:</l>
                  <l>For, not alone, high <hi>Palaces</hi> it rock'd,</l>
                  <l>But, alſo very dreadfully it knock'd</l>
                  <l>At ev'ry door; and made a ſignal ſpoile,</l>
                  <l>In ev'ry <hi>Shire</hi> and <hi>Province</hi> of this <hi>Iſle.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh! let us therefore ſearch out his <hi>intent;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, when he <hi>ſpeaks loud,</hi> there is ſomewhat meant</l>
                  <l>Deſerving more then ordinary heed,</l>
                  <l>Whereon (if ſleighted) miſchief will ſucceed.</l>
                  <l>He ſeldom, putteth forth a <hi>dreadful Voyce,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Save unto thoſe, whom nothing moves but <hi>Noyſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, if that, wakes them not, nor makes them fear him,</l>
                  <l>The next time, they ſhall <hi>feel</hi> him, ere they <hi>hear him.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let not a vain reſpect to <hi>Worms</hi> and <hi>Dust,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make us to GOD, and to <hi>our ſelves</hi> unjuſt:</l>
                  <l>For, what he <hi>acts,</hi> and <hi>how he doth proceed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We ought, in ev'ry <hi>Circumstance</hi> to heed,</l>
                  <l>Whomever it concerns, and nothing hide,</l>
                  <l>Whereby he may be duly <hi>glorifide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>men reform'd.</hi> Then, let us, ſince we may</l>
                  <l>Be dead to <hi>morrow, hear his Voyce to day.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We have had <hi>many days,</hi> wherein, he hath</l>
                  <l>Shewn <hi>Mercy,</hi> and forewarn'd us of his <hi>wrath.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometimes, in <hi>Calm-ſtill voyces,</hi> he doth ſpeak;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, in <hi>whirl-winds,</hi> which the Rocks do break;</l>
                  <l>As once 'twas ſayd to <hi>Iſr'el</hi> heretofore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then what he hath done, what ſhould he do more?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We have had <hi>many days,</hi> wherein, we made</l>
                  <l>Both <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> which acceptance had;</l>
                  <l>In them we made ſome ſhews of <hi>penitence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For that, which gave him cauſe to take offence,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116015:22"/>
                  <l>And for an <hi>Ahab-like humiliation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD, of his <hi>dooms,</hi> vouchſaf'd a mitigation;</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſtill, the very ſame, our <hi>Courſes</hi> be.</l>
                  <l>Now, GOD, will have his <hi>days</hi> as well as <hi>we.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He hath decreed a time, wherein, he will</l>
                  <l>As we have done our <hi>pleaſure,</hi> his fulfil;</l>
                  <l>And who can tell, how <hi>ſlowly,</hi> or how <hi>ſoon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, which he hath reſolved, ſhall be done?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What look we for? Lo, on a <hi>day of note,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Shepherd,</hi> our <hi>Protector,</hi> he hath ſmote.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Prince,</hi> of whom our <hi>own</hi> and <hi>neighb'ring Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had great <hi>proofs,</hi> and far greater <hi>expectations:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beyond his <hi>ſet day,</hi> if he ſpar'd not him,</l>
                  <l>How can we hope, he will defer our time?</l>
                  <l>Who knows, but that, if it ſucceeded thus</l>
                  <l>With him in <hi>one yeer, One yeer more</hi> to us</l>
                  <l>May be as fatal, if we ſtill put off</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Repentance,</hi> and at this <hi>fore-warning ſcoff?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Protector,</hi> and ye <hi>Counſellors of State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be therefore wiſe, before it be too late:</l>
                  <l>Ye <hi>Princes,</hi> and ye <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Learn, and obſerve what GOD hath now in hand:</l>
                  <l>And all ye <hi>people</hi> throughout theſe <hi>three Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take notice of thoſe dreadful <hi>Viſitations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which are portended, that, they may be made</l>
                  <l>Quite voyd, and have <hi>Effects</hi> to make you glad.</l>
                  <l>Truſt not in <hi>Riches,</hi> for, they wings have got,</l>
                  <l>And, will flie off, when you ſuſpect it not.</l>
                  <l>Truſt not in <hi>Earthly Power;</hi> for 'twill at length,</l>
                  <l>Break, and be ruined, by its <hi>own ſtrength.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Truſt not in <hi>Princes;</hi> For you can of none</l>
                  <l>Have more hopes, then you had of him that's gone;</l>
                  <l>But, truſt him, who, doth no mans truſt deceive;</l>
                  <l>Of whom nor <hi>Death,</hi> nor ought elſe can bereave;</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116015:22"/>
                  <l>And, vvho, nor <hi>Love,</hi> nor <hi>Power,</hi> nor <hi>wiſdom</hi> lacks</l>
                  <l>To finiſh, what for you he undertakes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Think, and ſpeak ſoberly of him that's gone;</l>
                  <l>For, he the <hi>work</hi> of GOD hath carry'd on,</l>
                  <l>So far as his appointed <hi>Station</hi> vvent;</l>
                  <l>And, being but a <hi>mortal Inſtrument</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made of the ſelf-ſame brittle <hi>earthen ſtuff,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That others are, was not, of ſo much proof</l>
                  <l>Againſt the baneful Flatteries of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſeem'd his true <hi>Friends,</hi> as againſt his <hi>Foes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In open Field, who could not act the part</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch as made their <hi>Batt'ries</hi> on his heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I look upon his <hi>Failings</hi> as mine own,</l>
                  <l>And neither whilſt he lived made them known,</l>
                  <l>(Nor will diſcloſe them further being dead)</l>
                  <l>But, that the <hi>living</hi> may be profited,</l>
                  <l>And that, GOD may be honour'd as he ought</l>
                  <l>By that which to remembrance ſhould be brought.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Conſcience</hi> bears me witneſs that I know</l>
                  <l>No malice, in my heart againſt a <hi>Foe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Much leſs againſt a <hi>Friend,</hi> vvhom I profeſt</l>
                  <l>To ſerve; and vvho, to his <hi>own Intereſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(In what he from the right-way did decline)</l>
                  <l>Did much more injury, then unto <hi>mine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Deeds,</hi> were all the means I had</l>
                  <l>To know him by; and what Reſult was made</l>
                  <l>By me thereon, I did ſince his deceaſe</l>
                  <l>Thus briefly in an <hi>Epitaph</hi> expreſs,</l>
                  <l>Which here I'll add, the <hi>Cenſures</hi> to prevent</l>
                  <l>Both of the <hi>Flatt'rer</hi> and <hi>Malevolent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who (in a manner) crucifie his <hi>Name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Betwixt a <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>In-glorious Fame</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As much as may be, to advance <hi>ſelf-ends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And nullifie, what GOD, thereby intends.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sequence_of_poems">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116015:23"/>
               <head>The EPITAPH.</head>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>HEre</hi> Dead <hi>He lies; who,</hi> Living <hi>here,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Was</hi> Britain's <hi>greateſt</hi> Hope <hi>and</hi> Fear.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, by what was on Him beſtown,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Had all His Equals over-grown:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His</hi> Predeceſſor's <hi>Sins and our,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Made way for Him to</hi> Soveraign Power;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By rendring that an Act of</hi> Reaſon</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Juſtice, <hi>which had elſe been</hi> Treaſon.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No</hi> Prince, <hi>was ever heretofore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>More</hi> praiſed, <hi>or</hi> diſpraiſed <hi>more.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Advantages, <hi>few ever won</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So great: None loſt ſo great a one.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This</hi> World <hi>afford no</hi> Pattern <hi>can</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which better ſhews what is in Man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His</hi> Vertues, <hi>were mough to do,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So much as GOD deſign'd Him to.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He</hi> Failings <hi>had: But, when liv'd any</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That had not every way as many,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If he (whilſt here abode he made)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such</hi> Tempters <hi>and</hi> Temptations <hi>had?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Preſume <hi>not therefore; but with</hi> Fear</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Minde, what you know, and ſee, and hear:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yea heed, what GOD, and Men have done,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But judge none but</hi> your ſelves <hi>alone;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And aim in chief, how to increaſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GOD's Glory, and the</hi> Publick Peace.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>This <hi>Change,</hi> and failing of our Expectations,</l>
                     <l>In many ſev'ral Things, which have Relations</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116015:23"/>
                     <l>To Us and Him, forewarn us to purſue</l>
                     <l>Some ſpeedy Courſe, Confuſion to eſchew,</l>
                     <l>And fortifie our <hi>Peace:</hi> But, what to do</l>
                     <l>Few know, or vvhat vvill beſt conduce thereto;</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhall know, till a <hi>Parliament</hi> convenes</l>
                     <l>To ſearch vvhat GOD, this <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp; <hi>People</hi> means.</l>
                     <l>In order to their wiſh'd-for <hi>Settlement,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>State</hi> hath choſe another <hi>Inſtrument,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whom GOD, hath in the room of <hi>OLIVER,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Permitted to be his <hi>Probationer.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Prudence, this <hi>Expedient</hi> they have us'd,</l>
                     <l>Leſt our <hi>Confuſions,</hi> growing more confus'd,</l>
                     <l>Might bring in <hi>Anarchy:</hi> And if they now,</l>
                     <l>Purſue vvhat GOD's, and <hi>humane Laws</hi> allow,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall not <hi>Arbitrarily</hi> proceed</l>
                     <l>Ought further, then <hi>unqueſtionable Need</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Neceſſitates, till thoſe things on their <hi>Baſis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are fixed, vvhich vvere thruſt out of their places:</l>
                     <l>It may in little time, conduce to that</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Men of ſingle Heart,</hi> have aimed at.</l>
                     <l>But, <hi>who,</hi> or <hi>what,</hi> vvill henceforth be a Bar</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Sequel</hi> muſt declare,</l>
                     <l>And vvill make manifeſt, vvhat <hi>Mask</hi> ſoever</l>
                     <l>It put upon an oppoſite Endeavour.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If he hath conſcientiouſly been choſe,</l>
                     <l>(Which none but GOD and his <hi>Electors</hi> knows)</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Peace,</hi> by this <hi>Prince,</hi> vvill be further'd more,</l>
                     <l>Then by him vvhom vve vvrought vvith heretofore.</l>
                     <l>Although he brings not ſuch <hi>APPEARANCES</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Either for His, or Our Advantages,</l>
                     <l>As did his <hi>Predeceſſor:</hi> for vve may</l>
                     <l>Finde thoſe <hi>Defects</hi> ſupplide another vvay;</l>
                     <l>Yea, vvant perhaps, of what the former had</l>
                     <l>In ſome kindes, may to our advantage add.</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116015:24"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Time,</hi> oft diſcovers in a timely ſeaſon,</l>
                     <l>What cannot be till then diſcern'd by <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wiſe <hi>Samuel,</hi> fail'd in his conjecturing</l>
                     <l>VVhich of the Sons of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> ſhould be <hi>King.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Man of War,</hi> now fitteſt for the <hi>Throne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some thought; but, vve behold inſtal'd thereon</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Man of Peace:</hi> And if in his <hi>Probations</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He bide the <hi>Teſt,</hi> he ſhall be to theſe <hi>Nations,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Fortreſs of Defence,</hi> in ſpight of thoſe,</l>
                     <l>VVho, in his <hi>Government,</hi> ſhall him oppoſe;</l>
                     <l>Provided, vve obſtruct not <hi>Providence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By perſevering in impenitence.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Supreme Title,</hi> is on him confer'd,</l>
                     <l>And, by vvhat vvay ſoe'er it vvas acquir'd,</l>
                     <l>That, for the preſent vvith a <hi>Soveraign Pow'r</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inveſts him; and vvhatever we call our,</l>
                     <l>Is in his hands, vvith all th' Authority</l>
                     <l>VVhich <hi>Scepters, Globes,</hi> or <hi>Crowns</hi> do ſignifie.</l>
                     <l>And, of that Dignity he ſtands poſſeſt</l>
                     <l>(By GOD's permiſſive Providence, at leaſt)</l>
                     <l>Not that he ſhould Uſurp, or challenge them,</l>
                     <l>As due unto his <hi>Fathers Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Him;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But, being forfeited by our <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Them, in his hands he hath by ſequeſtration,</l>
                     <l>To be ſecur'd there, till by <hi>Penitences,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>pardon,</hi> be ſu'd out, for our Offences,</l>
                     <l>That, vvhat, by <hi>Natures Law,</hi> and by GOD's <hi>Word,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To us belongeth, may be then reſtor'd:</l>
                     <l>For, GOD, Almighty, to no other ends,</l>
                     <l>Such <hi>Seizures,</hi> by a Soveraign <hi>Prince</hi> intends:</l>
                     <l>Save when, on <hi>wicked Nations</hi> he beſtowes</l>
                     <l>A <hi>wicked Prince,</hi> for both their overthrows.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If to GOD's ends, he Quadrate his Deſire,</l>
                     <l>He, ſhall become, far greater then his <hi>Sire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116015:24"/>
                     <l>He ſhall do nobler things, then ere he did;</l>
                     <l>More he ſhall <hi>Conquer,</hi> then he conquerred:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Affairs,</hi> which he of whom vve are bereft,</l>
                     <l>Both <hi>difficult</hi> and in confuſion left,</l>
                     <l>He ſhall reduce to Order; not alone</l>
                     <l>Subduing <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Realms,</hi> as he hath done,</l>
                     <l>But conquer alſo, thoſe <hi>deſtructive Evils,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which would deſtroy all, and triumph o'er <hi>Devils.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, though he had been, either by his <hi>Youth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By <hi>Flatterers,</hi> pretending zeal to Truth,</l>
                     <l>Or if he by a carnal <hi>Hope</hi> or fear</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Danger,</hi> had been tempted to adhere</l>
                     <l>To thoſe <hi>Deſigns,</hi> which under fair pretences,</l>
                     <l>May, to the <hi>Publick Rights,</hi> do violences;</l>
                     <l>Yet, if he ſhall conform to GOD, and them,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Counſel,</hi> he ſhould not contemn;</l>
                     <l>It ſhall (by much) a greater honour do him,</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Scepters, Crowns,</hi> and <hi>Thrones,</hi> can add unto him.</l>
                     <l>Yea, if upon the day of his <hi>Probation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He to the <hi>Supreme Council</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Aſſembled lawfully, and duly choſe)</l>
                     <l>Shall rather hearken, then give ear to thoſe</l>
                     <l>Who flatter him in ſecret; they ſhall never</l>
                     <l>Forſake him, but his <hi>Servants</hi> be for ever.</l>
                     <l>It ſhall on him, confer more <hi>Happineſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then, I in words, abm able to expreſs.</l>
                     <l>VVin him more <hi>Love</hi> then can by gold be bought,</l>
                     <l>Bring in more <hi>Joy,</hi> keep <hi>Terrors</hi> better out,</l>
                     <l>And (whilſt on Earth he lives) ſecure him more,</l>
                     <l>Then if each ſingle Souldier vvere a ſcore;</l>
                     <l>And, were my Life, of value to be pledg'd</l>
                     <l>For that <hi>Adventure,</hi> it ſhould be ingag'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Contrary-wiſe, if he their <hi>Lore</hi> purſue</l>
                     <l>VVho will perſwade him, that all is his due</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116015:25"/>
                     <l>VVhich he can graſp; or ſhall inſtead of <hi>Law</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Imploy the ſword, to keep <hi>Free-Men</hi> in aw;</l>
                     <l>GOD, will ariſe; and none ſhall need to ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Remedy,</hi> by <hi>Violence,</hi> to contrive.</l>
                     <l>For if we vvait on him, and ſit but ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Submitting patiently unto his <hi>Will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Chief Oppreſſors</hi> he will cauſe to be</l>
                     <l>Their own deſtruction, and ſo ſet us free.</l>
                     <l>Or, make our <hi>Foes</hi> our <hi>Friends,</hi> and back reſtore</l>
                     <l>All that was taken from us heretofore.</l>
                     <l>By ſuch means, GOD in former times releaſt</l>
                     <l>His People, who by <hi>Tyrants</hi> were oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>As doth appear, by that which did befal</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Babylon,</hi> and in th' <hi>Egyptian-thral,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhere, not a man made uſe of <hi>hand,</hi> or <hi>tongue</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To free himſelf, by <hi>violence,</hi> from wrong,</l>
                     <l>Except by <hi>Prayers,</hi> which (although offence</l>
                     <l>It gives to ſome) is lawful <hi>violence.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, by ſome ſuch means when GOD's time is come,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Bondage,</hi> we ſhall be deliver'd from.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>GOD, hath a thouſand wayes, to break the <hi>pow'r</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of twentie thouſand <hi>Tyrants</hi> in an hour;</l>
                     <l>Yet, may prove many <hi>Tooles,</hi> till he finds <hi>one,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or, <hi>moe,</hi> to finiſh what he hath begun.</l>
                     <l>If this turn Edge, he, peradventure may</l>
                     <l>Take thoſe again, that have been <hi>flung away,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhich being purged in <hi>Afflictions Fire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVill, now be pliable to his Deſire.</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Actings,</hi> vvhom vve now impow'red ſee,</l>
                     <l>VVill ſhortly, evidently ſignal be,</l>
                     <l>Of what ſhall follow: But, I fear th' event,</l>
                     <l>VVill not produce a happy <hi>Settlement,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till our <hi>Truſtees,</hi> Elected ſhall appear</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Conſcience-ſake,</hi> more then for <hi>Belly-Cheer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116015:25"/>
                     <l>Or ſuch-like <hi>by-reſpects;</hi> (by which we ſeem</l>
                     <l>To have our <hi>Birth-Rights</hi> in a mean eſteem:)</l>
                     <l>And, till, GOD, likewiſe, hath by Lot a <hi>Voice,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(As well as men) both in the future <hi>Choice</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of our <hi>protectors;</hi> and of others too,</l>
                     <l>Who muſt help act the work that's yet to do.</l>
                     <l>But, this will be no pleaſing Propoſition</l>
                     <l>To Avarice, Self-ſeeking and Ambition.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There's yet a <hi>Signe</hi> (to which things fore-expreſt</l>
                     <l>Relation have) more ſignal then the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Which, if it ſhall continue as it hath</l>
                     <l>Continu'd, will add <hi>Vengeance,</hi> unto <hi>Wrath;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, what vain hope ſoever, we may cheriſh,</l>
                     <l>VVe, with our <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> ſhall periſh.</l>
                     <l>GOD, where this grows predominant, deſpiſes</l>
                     <l>All Vows, Tears, Prayers, Cries and Sacrifices,</l>
                     <l>Faſts and Thankſgivings: For, he findes them all</l>
                     <l>VVhere this remains, but <hi>Hypocritical.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This is that <hi>Signe,</hi> which did in ev'ry Age,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe irrevocable <hi>Fore-Dooms</hi> preſage,</l>
                     <l>That introduc'd the <hi>final Deſolations,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of all thoſe mighty <hi>Empires, Kings</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhereof there's little left now, but a Name,</l>
                     <l>Preſerv'd among us by an empty <hi>Fame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For our <hi>Examples:</hi> This is that which ſhook</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Thrones,</hi> their <hi>Crowns</hi> defac'd, their <hi>Scepters</hi> broke:</l>
                     <l>Yet, this <hi>Signe</hi> is upon us, at this day;</l>
                     <l>From us, with ſpeed, remove it LORD, away.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>You look, as men expecting I ſhould ſhow</l>
                     <l>VVhat <hi>Signe</hi> that is. Good GOD! what do you know</l>
                     <l>If this you know not? Do you not behold</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Signe,</hi> by what I have already told?</l>
                     <l>Are you aſleep Friends? have you neither <hi>Ears</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor <hi>Eyes,</hi> that, undiſcern'd this yet appears?</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116015:26"/>
                     <l>Do you not hear the <hi>Groans</hi> of Men diſtreſt?</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Loud-loud Cries,</hi> of thoſe who are oppreſt?</l>
                     <l>Nor what a <hi>ſad Complaint</hi> atteſted ſtands</l>
                     <l>This day, by many hundreds of their hands?</l>
                     <l>Have you not heard, how <hi>Pris'ners</hi> do complain?</l>
                     <l>Nor ſeen what Tears are poured out in vain</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Widdows</hi> and poor <hi>Orphanes?</hi> ſee ye not</l>
                     <l>What vaſt Eſtates are by <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> got,</l>
                     <l>To their undoing, who their <hi>Lively-hood,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Fathers, Husbands,</hi> or their <hi>Brothers</hi> Blood</l>
                     <l>Loſt for the <hi>Publick?</hi> ſee you not how ſad</l>
                     <l>(Poor ſouls) they are? how lean, and how unclad?</l>
                     <l>Have you not heard a <hi>Mercileſs-Decree</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Condemn the <hi>Juſt,</hi> and ſet the <hi>Wicked</hi> free?</l>
                     <l>Do you not ſee, that, hundreds of <hi>Petitions</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have many yeers made known Mens ſad conditions,</l>
                     <l>Without <hi>Compaſſion?</hi> and what diſ-regard</l>
                     <l>Befalls them, who have merited reward?</l>
                     <l>Obſerve you not, that they, who made complaints</l>
                     <l>Ev'n unto thoſe who are eſteemed Saints,</l>
                     <l>Finde them as ſenſleſs of their ſaddeſt moans,</l>
                     <l>As men hew'd out of <hi>Blocks,</hi> or carv'd in <hi>ſtones?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, that <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> (in GOD's account</l>
                     <l>The worſt of ſins) is now grown Paramount?</l>
                     <l>Have you not ſeen <hi>Blood,</hi> as if water ſpilt,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Black Deſignes</hi> with <hi>Golden Colours</hi> guilt?</l>
                     <l>Nor many <hi>foul Offences</hi> made appear</l>
                     <l>As if they <hi>meritorious Actions</hi> were?</l>
                     <l>Perceive you not, who joyning are together,</l>
                     <l>VVho <hi>give</hi> and <hi>take Pow'r,</hi> to and from each other,</l>
                     <l>To re-infringe our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, by pretending Zeal to <hi>Piety,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Civil peace,</hi> advance the <hi>Intereſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of our old Foe, the <hi>Seven-headed Beaſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116015:26"/>
                     <l>VVith his <hi>Falſe Prophet?</hi> and invented have</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Grin,</hi> both <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> to inſlave?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Perceive you not, that <hi>Importunities,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhich made one from his Bed and Children riſe,</l>
                     <l>(And mov'd a <hi>Judge,</hi> who fear'd not GOD nor <hi>Men</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Prevails not now, as it prevailed then?</l>
                     <l>And, that, Mens <hi>tender Mercies</hi> are become</l>
                     <l>More cruel, then their <hi>Cruelties</hi> to ſome?</l>
                     <l>Nay, ſee you not, this <hi>Signe</hi> more ſignal made</l>
                     <l>By that, which our <hi>Apoſtacies</hi> now add?</l>
                     <l>And, that, this day, we do apparently</l>
                     <l>Stand guilty of the great'ſt <hi>Apostacie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From our firſt <hi>Covenants, Vows</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then ever could be charged on theſe <hi>Nations?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Obſerve you not, what fooliſh <hi>Propheſies</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVe take up? how, of <hi>Fictions</hi> and of <hi>Lies</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVe make us <hi>Refuges,</hi> as heretofore</l>
                     <l>They did, whoſe <hi>Paper-Works,</hi> we down have tore?</l>
                     <l>And how the lying Prophets and the <hi>Prieſts</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Comply, to ſave their carnal <hi>Intereſts?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have you not lately taken obſervation,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Laws</hi> by groſs, have had a confirmation,</l>
                     <l>Of which there's nothing on Record, (or little)</l>
                     <l>To warrant them, except their <hi>Names</hi> or Title?</l>
                     <l>And heed you not what <hi>Miſchieves</hi> that abuſe</l>
                     <l>VVith ſuch-like, may inſenſibly produce?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVell, GOD, forgive us all; for I believe</l>
                     <l>Theſe things you may apparently perceive.</l>
                     <l>But, if you ſhall make doubt, whether or no</l>
                     <l>It be, as I believe, or elſe, not ſo,</l>
                     <l>To GOD Himſelf, for tryal I'll appeal,</l>
                     <l>And, to the <hi>People</hi> of this <hi>Commonweal,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVho, know what's done, and will not be afraid</l>
                     <l>To juſtifie what may be truly ſaid.</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116015:27"/>
                     <l>For, when this Signe is fix'd; though men look high</l>
                     <l>Or big, it ſhews <hi>Deſtruction</hi> draweth nigh.</l>
                     <l>Yea, though the <hi>proud</hi> may ſeemingly contemn</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Signe,</hi> it will impreſſions leave on them:</l>
                     <l>For, horrid <hi>inward Pangs,</hi> and <hi>ſecret Dread</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVill ſeize upon their Hearts, when this is read;</l>
                     <l>And that great <hi>Storm</hi> of Brimſtone, Fire, and Snares,</l>
                     <l>VVhich GOD, for men impenitent prepares,</l>
                     <l>VVill oft to minde be brought; and waking keep</l>
                     <l>Their eyes, ſometimes, when they deſire to ſleep.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But to be plain (why ſhould there be a doubt</l>
                     <l>Of that whereof, Proofs need not to be brought?)</l>
                     <l>I, ſee the want of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(The moſt apparent <hi>Signe</hi> of <hi>Deſolation</hi>)</l>
                     <l>So evident; that, I, do boldly here</l>
                     <l>Before GOD, <hi>Men and Angels,</hi> witneſſe bear</l>
                     <l>That our Oppreſſions are at this day more</l>
                     <l>Then ere I knew them at one time before,</l>
                     <l>Since firſt I knew the world; though I have been</l>
                     <l>No ſtranger where mens actings beſt are ſeen;</l>
                     <l>And, where I ſaw (for their and our Offences)</l>
                     <l>Six <hi>Parliaments</hi> cut off by <hi>Violences,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or by untimely ends, within the ſpace</l>
                     <l>Of theſe laſt twenty years, and ſomewhat leſs:</l>
                     <l>Yea, though I've ſeen <hi>two</hi> Governments arow</l>
                     <l>Deſtroyed for <hi>Injuſtice;</hi> and ſee now</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Third</hi> indanger'd; which thus makes me ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>And like the Son of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> forth to break</l>
                     <l>Into expreſſions beyond Expectation,</l>
                     <l>To make men ſeek their timely Preſervation.</l>
                     <l>For this <hi>Signe</hi> is ſo fatal, that unleſs</l>
                     <l>It quickly be remov'd by <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Brotherly Compaſſion,</hi> we ſhall never</l>
                     <l>Enjoy that Peace for which we do endeavor.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116015:27"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some, naytheleſs, will judge me worthy blame</l>
                     <l>And puniſhment, thus to diſcloſe the ſhame</l>
                     <l>Of this my <hi>Nation;</hi> and, I ſhould confeſs</l>
                     <l>That for ſo doing, I deſerv'd no leſs,</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Malice</hi> had inclin'd me thereunto;</l>
                     <l>Or, if I ought have aggravated ſo,</l>
                     <l>That it exceedeth <hi>Truth;</hi> or, if o'er-blown</l>
                     <l>Theſe <hi>Crimes</hi> had been, unleſs by me made known.</l>
                     <l>But, 'tis not ſo, nor ſo; And, if he may</l>
                     <l>Deſerve the Rod, who doth but write or ſay</l>
                     <l>What is miſ-done, (and ſpeaks it with intent</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Miſchieves which may follow to prevent)</l>
                     <l>What merit they, who act them without care</l>
                     <l>Of what ſad things, they certain Symptomes are?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That this bears Date the laſt day of <hi>December</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In <hi>ſixteen hundred fifty eight,</hi> remember;</l>
                     <l>And, that a <hi>Reconcilement</hi> be before</l>
                     <l>VVe have provok'd GOD's Patience, one yeer more;</l>
                     <l>Leſt, I <hi>my ſelf,</hi> be made another <hi>Signe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of what the former <hi>Symptomes</hi> pre-divine.</l>
                     <l>For, thoſe <hi>Confuſions</hi> VVhich diſtract this <hi>Sate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are typiſied in my <hi>outward Fate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And printed on me, by that violation</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which defiles this Generation.</l>
                     <l>They ſeem to have enough in outward ſhow,</l>
                     <l>To bear their <hi>Port,</hi> to pay the Debts they ow,</l>
                     <l>And for the future a ſufficiency:</l>
                     <l>So alſo, if I had my Right, have I.</l>
                     <l>As (notwithſtanding this) with much ado</l>
                     <l>They, now ſubſiſt: So, fares it with me too.</l>
                     <l>As, at the preſent, their <hi>Expences</hi> be</l>
                     <l>More then their <hi>Incomes;</hi> So it is with me.</l>
                     <l>They have more <hi>Foes</hi> then <hi>Friends;</hi> And much I am</l>
                     <l>Deceived, if I may not ſay the ſame.</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116015:28"/>
                     <l>My <hi>Foes</hi> and <hi>troubles</hi> in another year</l>
                     <l>May ruine me; and ſo will theirs I fear</l>
                     <l>If he on whoſe aſſiſtance I depend</l>
                     <l>Prevents not what their Foes and mine intend,</l>
                     <l>Before another yeer wheels round, I may</l>
                     <l>Enjoy an <hi>outward peace;</hi> And ſo ſhall they,</l>
                     <l>If they embrace the means, that will be ſhown,</l>
                     <l>And, follow not <hi>Devices</hi> of their own.</l>
                     <l>Yea, that perhaps, which will to them betide,</l>
                     <l>Shall in my <hi>Lot,</hi> be firſt <hi>pretypifide.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If <hi>timely Juſtice,</hi> be vouchſaf'd to me,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>timely Mercies,</hi> they reliev'd ſhall be:</l>
                     <l>If I, permitted am to be deſtroy'd,</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>power,</hi> may not long after be enjoy'd:</l>
                     <l>And GOD ſo much incenſed may appear</l>
                     <l>(As with the <hi>Jews</hi> once) that, he none will hear</l>
                     <l>But for himſelf, who ere from thenceforth ſtands</l>
                     <l>Within the <hi>Gaps,</hi> to keep Plagues from theſe Lands.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thus, in plain language, and in homely Rimes</l>
                     <l>You have a brief Character of theſe <hi>times,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Made on a <hi>ſleight occaſion;</hi> to awake</l>
                     <l>The drowzie; that more heedful, it may make</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Men heedleſs;</hi> and him to be ſomewhat wiſer</l>
                     <l>Who is not of <hi>good Counſel,</hi> a <hi>Deſpiſer.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Souldiers dream,</hi> but of a <hi>barly-Cake</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Told to his fellow, when he did awake,</l>
                     <l>And Spirited with his <hi>Interpretation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Produced an <hi>Effect,</hi> worth obſervation;</l>
                     <l>And ſo may this, although to ſome, it ſeem,</l>
                     <l>No better then a ſilly Souldiers <hi>dream.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll add no more (though much more add I might)</l>
                     <l>For, here will be too much for them to ſleight,</l>
                     <l>Who, in thoſe <hi>Flatt'ries,</hi> much more pleaſure have</l>
                     <l>That ſend them with diſhonour to the <hi>Grave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116015:28"/>
                     <l>Then in plain ſpoken <hi>Truths,</hi> which would to them</l>
                     <l>Have brought <hi>ſalvation,</hi> if embrac'd in time.</l>
                     <l>And here, will be enough to ſtartle ſome,</l>
                     <l>To ſtir up others, till th' <hi>Alarum</hi> come</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a <hi>number,</hi> as may then ſuffice</l>
                     <l>To make a <hi>reconciling Sacrifice.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Unleſs we <hi>Sodom-like,</hi> ſtand unreform'd</l>
                     <l>Until with <hi>Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> we are <hi>ſtorm'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This SALT, made out of SALT, I took occaſion</l>
                     <l>To boyl up, for the ſervice of my <hi>Nation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To this height, as conceiving it was meet</l>
                     <l>To keep what's yet <hi>unputrified</hi> ſweet,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe corrupted humors to expel</l>
                     <l>Which in GOD's noſtrils have an evil ſmel.</l>
                     <l>I hope, men will not throw it in mine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Neither ſo univerſally deſpiſe</l>
                     <l>Theſe timely <hi>warnings,</hi> that they ſhall by <hi>none</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To good effect, be read, and thought upon:</l>
                     <l>And, if but <hi>two or three,</hi> ſhall thereby gain</l>
                     <l>Some benefit, I have not loſt my pain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mine be the ſhame,</hi> if I, hereby to him</l>
                     <l>Intend diſgrace, whoſe <hi>Verſes,</hi> are my <hi>Theam.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I did but thus, his <hi>Mercury</hi> calcine</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Phyſick;</hi> Let him do as much by <hi>mine;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, if, ought from my <hi>failings,</hi> he deduce</l>
                     <l>Which may to others, be of wholſom uſe,</l>
                     <l>I, ſhall be pleas'd; becauſe, what loſe I may</l>
                     <l>In one kind, will be gain'd another way.</l>
                     <l>But, if he hath, ſo generous a minde</l>
                     <l>As to believe he hath, I am inclinde,</l>
                     <l>He will return me thanks, that I have us'd</l>
                     <l>To no worſe purpoſe, that which he hath mus'd.</l>
                     <l>Yea, and rejoyce, that, what in ſport he writ,</l>
                     <l>This needful <hi>premonition</hi> did beget.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116015:29"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WHen I had pen'd this, and o'erview'd the ſame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therewith conſid'ring what a</hi> worm <hi>I am,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What</hi> they <hi>are, who, offence thereat may take;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What miſconstructions,</hi> Prejudice <hi>may make;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With what</hi> ſcorn <hi>and</hi> contempt <hi>it may be read;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, having therewithal conſidered</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That, I, am one adhering to no</hi> Faction,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To give me countenance in ſuch an Action.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor having in my ſelf, pow'r to defend me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From Injuries, nor</hi> Patron <hi>to befriend me;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It quail'd my</hi> Courage; <hi>and I'll not diſſemble,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It made my</hi> heart <hi>ake, and my</hi> Fleſh <hi>to tremble.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And I had hid my</hi> Talent <hi>in the ground,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs, a timely</hi> Cordial <hi>had been found.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But, he who gave it, my faint heart reviv'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From him, new</hi> Reſolutions <hi>I receiv'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wherewith confirm'd, my</hi> Soul <hi>to him addreſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such</hi> Muſings, <hi>as are next, in</hi> Words <hi>expreſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>LORD GOD, if, to thy-<hi>glory,</hi> this may tend,</l>
                     <l>Give it, ſome way a <hi>Paſport</hi> to that end,</l>
                     <l>And ſet thy <hi>Imprimatur</hi> thereupon;</l>
                     <l>For, <hi>Thou haſt done</hi> it, if it be well done:</l>
                     <l>If it be ſuch, as will not honour thee,</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>mine,</hi> and as <hi>mine,</hi> let it ſmother'd be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I feel a <hi>ſtrong perſwaſion,</hi> in my minde,</l>
                     <l>That, hereunto, I was by thee inclinde</l>
                     <l>And, that, there may be ſomewhat more expreſt,</l>
                     <l>Whereby, <hi>thine,</hi> and the <hi>Publike Intereſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May be advanced; which if it be ſo,</l>
                     <l>And, thou ſhalt pleaſe, to call me thereunto,</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116015:29"/>
                     <l>By giving me a <hi>Spirit,</hi> that may fit</l>
                     <l>So weak an <hi>Agent,</hi> to adventure it,</l>
                     <l>I'll proſecute it home, although it ſhall</l>
                     <l>Coſt all, which in this <hi>World,</hi> I <hi>mine</hi> can call.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I have been ſubject to ſome Heſitations,</l>
                     <l>Through pity, to thoſe dear and near <hi>Relations,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which thou on me beſtow'dſt; and thereby, have</l>
                     <l>Loſt much, which by that means, I thought to ſave,</l>
                     <l>To make me take more heed, <hi>by,</hi> and <hi>from whom</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All things that ſhall advantage me, muſt come:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Them,</hi> therefore, henceforth, I reſolve to truſt</l>
                     <l>To thy diſpoſal, whom, I knew ſo juſt,</l>
                     <l>That, thou of thoſe, unmindful canſt not be,</l>
                     <l>Who truly place their <hi>Confidence</hi> on thee:</l>
                     <l>And, now to fix in me, a <hi>Confidence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For time to come, upon thy <hi>Providence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By thoſe <hi>Experiments,</hi> which I have ſeen,</l>
                     <l>I will confeſs, what <hi>thou,</hi> to <hi>me</hi> haſt been.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So univerſally thou doſt extend</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>Love,</hi> that, all men it doth comprehend,</l>
                     <l>Who ſhall not wilfully reject thy <hi>Grace,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When thou, to them ſhalt offer an <hi>embrace;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, all things doſt vouchſafe, which may enable</l>
                     <l>To <hi>honour thee,</hi> or make <hi>life comfortable,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So far, as we may <hi>carnal things poſſeſs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Without obſtructing, our <hi>chief happineſs.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To evidence this <hi>gratiouſneſs</hi> of thine,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>living mans experience</hi> outgoes <hi>mine:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For, ev'ry <hi>Faculty</hi> of mine hath heard</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>wondrous Mercies,</hi> thereunto declar'd</l>
                     <l>In its <hi>own language,</hi> to th' intelligence</l>
                     <l>As well of every <hi>Paſſión,</hi> and each <hi>ſenſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As of my <hi>Reaſon;</hi> ſo, that I can ſay</l>
                     <l>They have to me, abounded ev'ry way.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116015:30"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſince I knew the <hi>World</hi> (ev'n ever ſince)</l>
                     <l>Thine, <hi>extraordinary providence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath watched over me; and, I, from none</l>
                     <l>Have had <hi>ſubſiſtence,</hi> but, from thee alone;</l>
                     <l>Or, by <hi>thoſe,</hi> whom no <hi>temporal Relation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could move thereto, without thine Invitation;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Kind'red</hi> have been to me, in <hi>wants</hi> and <hi>dangers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If not my Foes, at beſt, more ſtrange then <hi>Strangers:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, not the ſmalleſt portion of my <hi>wrong</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath from their <hi>malice,</hi> or their <hi>envie</hi> ſprung.</l>
                     <l>Few have been more Cenſorious of my <hi>ways,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or, apter to believe what <hi>malice</hi> ſays.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That, which my <hi>ſecret Foes</hi> deſigned had,</l>
                     <l>To ruine my eſtate, thereto did add;</l>
                     <l>And, through thy <hi>mercy,</hi> more unto me gave</l>
                     <l>Then ere I got, by all the <hi>Friends</hi> I have.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Friendſhips</hi> acquired by mine own endeavor,</l>
                     <l>And, all my <hi>own works,</hi> have been fruitleſs ever;</l>
                     <l>Except it were, to bring thoſe <hi>troubles</hi> on me,</l>
                     <l>Which have no leſs then <hi>twice</hi> or <hi>thrice undone me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And made work for thy <hi>Mercy. Thrice,</hi> thou haſt</l>
                     <l>Redeem'd me, when in Priſon I was caſt</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Supreme Pow'r;</hi> and freed me without <hi>ſhame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When I was threatned, by the voyce of Fame</l>
                     <l>With loſs of limb and tortures, and knew none</l>
                     <l>On whom I could rely but thee alone.</l>
                     <l>Through <hi>dangers,</hi> into <hi>ſafety,</hi> thou haſt led me;</l>
                     <l>And, when I wanted meat, by <hi>Ravens</hi> fed me.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Twice,</hi> nigh as poor as <hi>Job,</hi> I have been made;</l>
                     <l>And ev'ry time, that, which was loſt, I had</l>
                     <l>To me returned double; without cheating</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Common-Wealth;</hi> or private men defeating,</l>
                     <l>Of what to them belonged; Nor, by <hi>wiving,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Which is to ſome, a ſudden way of thriving)</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:116015:30"/>
                     <l>Was my <hi>Eſtate repair'd;</hi> nor thereunto,</l>
                     <l>Did I, by fawning upon <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Foe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Add ought; nor ever had a <hi>Legacy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To me bequeath'd, theſe <hi>loſſes</hi> to ſupply;</l>
                     <l>But, by ſuch <hi>means,</hi> that, if I ſhould declare it,</l>
                     <l>Few would, perhaps, believe it, when they hear it.</l>
                     <l>For, I confeſs, that I my ſelf do wonder,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>paſt,</hi> and <hi>preſent things,</hi> I duly ponder,</l>
                     <l>In what great <hi>Wants,</hi> I, without <hi>Want</hi> have liv'd,</l>
                     <l>And under what <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> I have thriv'd.</l>
                     <l>This makes the World, which hitherto hath grutcht</l>
                     <l>That, I, with what is hers ſhould be enricht,</l>
                     <l>(As many think I am) to wonder more</l>
                     <l>How I, whom ſhe intended to keep poor,</l>
                     <l>Subſiſt in her deſpight, then, how all they</l>
                     <l>Grew <hi>wealthy,</hi> who were <hi>beggars</hi> tother day:</l>
                     <l>And from her ſight, thy <hi>Bounty,</hi> being hid,</l>
                     <l>She thinks, I thrived, as her <hi>Servants</hi> did.</l>
                     <l>And, leaves no means unpractis'd, to deſtroy</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Competencie,</hi> which, I yet enjoy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When to be thought <hi>poor,</hi> it may do me ſhame,</l>
                     <l>(Or, make me poorer, then ſhe thinks I am)</l>
                     <l>She taketh all occaſions, then, to ſay</l>
                     <l>That, <hi>more I owe, then ever I can pay.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When to be deem'd <hi>rich,</hi> may deprive of that</l>
                     <l>Which is my <hi>due;</hi> ſhe <hi>trebles</hi> my <hi>Eſtate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But to prevent the <hi>miſchief,</hi> which thereby</l>
                     <l>Had elſe enſude, thou ſent'ſt in a <hi>ſupply;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, always, haſt enabled me, at leaſt</l>
                     <l>To bear the weight, wherewith, I was oppreſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou, likewiſe, kept'ſt me without ſhame of face,</l>
                     <l>Maugre <hi>Detractions,</hi> malice, when <hi>Diſgrace</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was <hi>then,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> intended, where it might</l>
                     <l>With moſt <hi>diſparagement,</hi> on me alight:</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:116015:31"/>
                     <l>And though but few, more ſcandaliz'd have been,</l>
                     <l>Few, of my <hi>Rank,</hi> have liv'd in more eſteem.</l>
                     <l>Thou, from the violence of great <hi>Oppreſſors</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Pietie</hi>'s, and <hi>Friendſhip</hi>'s, falſe Profeſſors</l>
                     <l>Haſt often ſav'd me; yea, and from the Rage</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe, to whom, I long ſince did preſage</l>
                     <l>VVhat they, and I, ſaw afterward inflicted,</l>
                     <l>According as my <hi>Muſes</hi> had predicted;</l>
                     <l>And, they, who then, for that, at me did rave,</l>
                     <l>Have many yeers, lain quiet in the <hi>Grave.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In that great <hi>Peſtilence</hi> (whereof no time</l>
                     <l>Hath mentioned the like, in this our <hi>Clime</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Thou did'ſt preſerve me, when on ev'ry ſide,</l>
                     <l>In ſhort time, many <hi>twenty thouſands</hi> dide,</l>
                     <l>Though underneath the ſelf-ſame Roof I lay,</l>
                     <l>VVhere many by that <hi>Plague</hi> were took away,</l>
                     <l>That I might leave that <hi>Judgement</hi> on record,</l>
                     <l>To them who were reſerved for the ſword:</l>
                     <l>And when the <hi>Sword</hi> was ſent his work to do,</l>
                     <l>From that, thy <hi>Mercy,</hi> did preſerve me too.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thou haſt, moreover, from the menacing</l>
                     <l>And dreadful Wrath of an <hi>incenſed King</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Deliver'd me, without a <hi>Mediator,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or back receding in the ſmalleſt matter,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Truths</hi> aver'd. Thou from th'unjuſt intent</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Evil Members</hi> in a <hi>Parliament</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did'ſt <hi>twice</hi> preſerve me: and, all thoſe <hi>Neglects,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and thoſe other ſad effects</l>
                     <l>Which I have ſuff'red, Demonſtrations be</l>
                     <l>VVhat, <hi>moſt men are,</hi> and what <hi>thou art to me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay (which is more then this) thou haſt, thereby</l>
                     <l>Not onely ſhewn to me the Vanity</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>other men;</hi> but alſo, made mine <hi>own</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deficiencies</hi> unto my ſelf, more known:</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:116015:31"/>
                     <l>And both my <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Follies</hi> to appear</l>
                     <l>More my advantage, then my <hi>Vertues</hi> were:</l>
                     <l>For, thoſe things, which the <hi>Devil</hi> to undo me</l>
                     <l>Deſign'd; and whereto <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> did wo me,</l>
                     <l>Thou mad'ſt to be a means of <hi>Preſervations</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From thoſe, and alſo, from the like <hi>Temptations;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all the <hi>troubles,</hi> which the world brings on me,</l>
                     <l>With thoſe great <hi>Injuries</hi> which have been done me,</l>
                     <l>(Inſtead of harming me) have in the Duſt</l>
                     <l>But tumbled me, to rub away the Ruſt;</l>
                     <l>Or been a neceſſary <hi>Diſcipline,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To fit me for thoſe <hi>Services</hi> of Thine,</l>
                     <l>VVhich elſe had been omitted to this day;</l>
                     <l>Or, if done, not ſo done, as now they may:</l>
                     <l>For which my Soul out of that Duſt doth raiſe</l>
                     <l>A Voice, in <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> to thy <hi>Praiſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet leſt, theſe thy <hi>great Mercies,</hi> might at length,</l>
                     <l>Prove ineffectual, by that little ſtrength</l>
                     <l>VVhich is in <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> if they vvere quite</l>
                     <l>Depriv'd of that, wherein they take delight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>,</hi> who know'ſt vvhat defects are in <hi>mans nature,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(And therefore art indulgent to thy <hi>Creature</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Haſt graciouſly been pleas'd to intermingle</l>
                     <l>VVhat might diſtaſte, or be unwholeſome ſingle;</l>
                     <l>So temp'ring <hi>ſweet</hi> vvith <hi>ſow'r,</hi> that I by neither</l>
                     <l>Might <hi>harm</hi> receive, but <hi>Good</hi> from both together:</l>
                     <l>And, vvhereſoe'er I live, doſt ſtill provide</l>
                     <l>To <hi>neighbour me,</hi> one of the <hi>Sons of Pride,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To make me vvatchful, and conſider vvell</l>
                     <l>VVhere I yet am; and, <hi>among whom</hi> I dwell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To me, Thou likewiſe haſt vouchſaf'd a ſhare</l>
                     <l>In vvhatſoever <hi>Pleaſant</hi> doth appear</l>
                     <l>To men of all <hi>Degrees,</hi> vvho grow not <hi>mad</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>drunk,</hi> by thoſe <hi>Delights,</hi> vvhich they have had:</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:116015:32"/>
                     <l>For <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> have to me</l>
                     <l>Made <hi>Common thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> more pleaſureful to be</l>
                     <l>Then their <hi>chief Dainties,</hi> vvho to that are born</l>
                     <l>VVhich muſt be <hi>won</hi> by others, ere 'tis <hi>worn;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVho have but ſuch <hi>Enjoyments</hi> at the beſt,</l>
                     <l>As they, who come full gorged to a <hi>Feaſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet, when of thoſe <hi>Delights,</hi> I am bereav'd,</l>
                     <l>By whoſe enjoyment, I content receiv'd;</l>
                     <l>They leave not, (when departing I do finde them)</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Bitterneſs</hi> upon my Soul behinde them;</l>
                     <l>But, give the better appetite to thoſe</l>
                     <l>Whoſe taſte, and pleaſure, I ſhall never loſe:</l>
                     <l>And LORD, it flows from thy <hi>great Mercy,</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>That, <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> ſhould willingly forgo</l>
                     <l>What <hi>conſtitutes themſelves,</hi> to place <hi>affection</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Upon an <hi>inconceivable Perfection.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though, (as Thou know'ſt) the world my <hi>Foe</hi> hath bin,</l>
                     <l>And, would afford me little ſhare therein;</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Portion</hi> I have alſo, there acquir'd</l>
                     <l>By thy <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> more then I once deſir'd:</l>
                     <l>And vvhen I coveted more to poſſeſs,</l>
                     <l>(Though by a lawful meanes,) thou mad'ſt it leſs,</l>
                     <l>To minde me, that, nought will with me indure,</l>
                     <l>Save what by Thy meer <hi>Bounty,</hi> I procure.</l>
                     <l>If, therefore, it be loſt, confeſs I muſt</l>
                     <l>That, Thy permiſſion of it will be juſt;</l>
                     <l>And, with contentment, I will let it go,</l>
                     <l>Though all the reſt, be taken from me too:</l>
                     <l>For, I moſt covet thoſe things to enjoy,</l>
                     <l>Which neither I, nor others can deſtroy:</l>
                     <l>And, though ſometime, Thy <hi>Cup</hi> imbitter'd be,</l>
                     <l>By thoſe diſtempers vvhich remain in me,</l>
                     <l>I take it, naytheleſs, with true <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And vvould not change my <hi>Lot</hi> with any living.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116015:32"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though out of <hi>Levity</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>I, ev'ry day, think, wiſh, and ſpeak, and do</l>
                     <l>Like other <hi>fooliſh Men:</hi> yet, if I know</l>
                     <l>Mine own Mind, though Thou vvould'ſt on me beſtow</l>
                     <l>All I could vviſh, for vviſhing; I vvould vvave</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Grant:</hi> and onely ask of Thee to have</l>
                     <l>VVhat Thou vvilt; and that Thou vvould'ſt take away</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Self-will,</hi> though my <hi>Life</hi> upon it lay:</l>
                     <l>For nought I now deſire, to <hi>have</hi> or <hi>be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But what may be beſt pleaſing unto <hi>Thee:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, if this <hi>temper</hi> could be ſtill retain'd,</l>
                     <l>Men vvould believe, vvhat they, yet, think is fain'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To fortifie my <hi>Faith,</hi> and that deſire</l>
                     <l>VVherewith, at preſent, Thou doſt me inſpire,</l>
                     <l>Thus of thy Mercies paſt, I have in part</l>
                     <l>Confeſſion made: and, if I know my heart,</l>
                     <l>I durſt not them before Thee thus aver,</l>
                     <l>VVho knoweſt all things, if untrue they vvere.</l>
                     <l>Yet, pardon my <hi>miſtakes,</hi> if any be,</l>
                     <l>And, make, what I conceive thou art to me,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Pledge,</hi> of what thou wilt be, to mine end.</l>
                     <l>Above all other <hi>Enemies,</hi> defend</l>
                     <l>And, ſave me from <hi>my ſelf:</hi> For, <hi>World</hi> nor <hi>Devil,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can then inflict upon me any evil,</l>
                     <l>That ſhall deprive me of ought <hi>tranſitory,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which may advance my <hi>welfare,</hi> or thy <hi>Glory.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Next to my <hi>ſelf,</hi> my <hi>ſecond-ſelf,</hi> and <hi>They</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who ſprung from <hi>us,</hi> do ſtand moſt in the way</l>
                     <l>To hinder me, in that, whereto, my <hi>minde</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perſwadeth me, it is by thee inclinde:</l>
                     <l>For, my reſpect to them, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                     <l>Oft, makes me guilty of <hi>faint-heartedneſs.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh! be ſo merciful to <hi>them</hi> and <hi>me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That, neither of us, may a Grievance be</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:116015:33"/>
                     <l>Unto each other, in vvhat doth pertain</l>
                     <l>To Thy <hi>Affairs,</hi> whilſt vve on Earth remain;</l>
                     <l>Or make us, vvith Reluctancy, to ſpare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our ſelves</hi> to ſerve Thee; Or, vvhat is more dear</l>
                     <l>To either, then <hi>our ſelves:</hi> But, give each other</l>
                     <l>To thee, that we in thee, may live together</l>
                     <l>VVhen we are called hence, and timely know</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Bliſs</hi> conſiſts not in things here below.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know, Thou art vvell pleas'd it ſhould be thus,</l>
                     <l>And that, hereto Thou wilt enable us:</l>
                     <l>For, though I feel them, to be ſomewhat neerer</l>
                     <l>Unto my <hi>Fleſh,</hi> Thou to my <hi>Soul</hi> art dearer;</l>
                     <l>And, as thou gav'ſt them vvhen they vvere deſir'd,</l>
                     <l>I'll back return them, vvhen they are requir'd,</l>
                     <l>VVith mine <hi>own Soul</hi> to boot: Do not diſpiſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This All;</hi> For, in theſe, <hi>All,</hi> I ſacrifice.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To Thee, for theſe <hi>Relations,</hi> I am Debter,</l>
                     <l>Then vvhich I know no man enjoyeth better,</l>
                     <l>VVho meriteth ſo little the poſſeſſing</l>
                     <l>Of any extraordinary <hi>Bleſſing.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet, if thou haſt a <hi>Work</hi> to call me to,</l>
                     <l>By which, I may my <hi>Self,</hi> and <hi>them</hi> undo,</l>
                     <l>I'll undertake it, ſo, Thou ſtand but by me,</l>
                     <l>And ſhalt thereto, with <hi>needful Pow'r</hi> ſupply me.</l>
                     <l>Yea, though Thou ſhalt no more Thy <hi>Bleſſings</hi> double</l>
                     <l>As heretofore; but waſte away in trouble</l>
                     <l>(By multiplied <hi>Sufferings, Wants,</hi> and <hi>Grief</hi>)</l>
                     <l>The remnant of my, yet, prolonged Life;</l>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd, that, I will never more</l>
                     <l>Thereat, repine again, as heretofore:</l>
                     <l>But onely pray, my <hi>Sins,</hi> may be forgiven,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Believe,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> and ſeek my <hi>LOT</hi> in Heav'n.</l>
                     <l>LORD, keep me in this minde; and then, let MAN,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>World, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Devil,</hi> do the worſt they can.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:116015:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sarcaſmus Aenigmaticus.</hi> Hereto is added the following <hi>Riddle,</hi> with the occaſion of compoſing it, as neither altogether impertinent to what precedes, nor to what is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled by this Portion of Scripture;</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Anſwer a Fool, according to his fooliſhneſs, leſt he be wiſe in his own conceit, <bibl>Prov. 26.5.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS well, to <hi>Foes,</hi> as <hi>Friends,</hi> I thought it fit</l>
                  <l>To ſhew this <hi>Poem,</hi> ere I publiſh'd it,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe a <hi>Foe,</hi> ſometimes, lets fall a word,</l>
                  <l>Which (heeded well) more <hi>Caution</hi> may afford</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>friendly Cenſurers:</hi> And, to that end,</l>
                  <l>When I to ſome had read what here is pen'd;</l>
                  <l>By them, propoſed <hi>jeering Queſtions</hi> were,</l>
                  <l>Fit for no Anſwer but by <hi>Counter-jeer.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet I will Anſwer them, when unto me</l>
                  <l>This following RIDDLE, ſhall unriddl'd be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>WHat may that be, which, when it is</hi> Expreſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is most</hi> Unknown? <hi>Is</hi> Worſt, <hi>when 'tis at</hi> Beſt?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And when it is at</hi> Greateſt, <hi>then 'tis</hi> Leaſt?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis Black and White, Red, Yellow, Blew and Green;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet,</hi> Underſtood, Felt, Smelt, Heard, Taſted, Seen;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neither</hi> now is, <hi>nor</hi> ſhall be, <hi>nor</hi> hath been.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116015:34"/>
                  <l>To any one, who tells me what it is,</l>
                  <l>That's anſwerable ev'ry way to this,</l>
                  <l>I do engage; and thereto ſet my hand,</l>
                  <l>To tell him any thing he doth demand.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>George Wither.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <l>PAge 1. line 20 for <hi>Vines,</hi> read <hi>Pines.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Page 9. line 25. for <hi>Super-added,</hi> read <hi>Superſeded.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Page 18. line 32. for <hi>becauſe,</hi> read <hi>became.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Page 22. line 8. for <hi>all,</hi> read <hi>of.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Page 23. line 11. for <hi>puff'd,</hi> read <hi>paſs.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Page 24. line 14. put out <hi>or.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:116015:34"/>
            <head>A <hi>bitter-ſweet</hi> Paſsion of the Soul, Expreſſed in A HYMNE to GOD. By The ſame AUTHOR.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY dear, my gracious GOD!</l>
               <l>From me, Thy <hi>Face,</hi> why hideſt Thou?</l>
               <l>Oh! why is Thy aboad</l>
               <l>So <hi>far,</hi> ſo <hi>long,</hi> removed now?</l>
               <l>See, how alone</l>
               <l>(Now Thou art gone)</l>
               <l>And helpleſs, I am left;</l>
               <l>Of ev'ry thing</l>
               <l>That joy may bring,</l>
               <l>Heed, how I am bereft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> I, who but lately ſeem'd</l>
               <l>Of many <hi>Friends</hi> belov'd to be,</l>
               <l>And, ſo of ſome eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>As if their <hi>Souls</hi> had liv'd in me;</l>
               <l>(Though, nor neglect,</l>
               <l>Nor diſ-reſpect,</l>
               <l>Of them deſerv'd I have)</l>
               <l>Am now, forlorn</l>
               <l>As one <hi>unborn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or lodged in his <hi>Grave.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116015:35"/>
            <lg>
               <l n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The lovely <hi>Deſart-Owl,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which dares not fly abroad by Day;</l>
               <l>That <hi>perſecuted Fowl,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For which the <hi>Fowler</hi> Snares doth lay;</l>
               <l>Is not <hi>hipt</hi> at,</l>
               <l>As I, of late,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Wag-Tayls, Dawes</hi> and <hi>Crows.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor hardlyer ſcapes</l>
               <l>His Gins and Traps</l>
               <l>Who ſeeks her overthrows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> For, when with ſome <hi>Delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My heart began on Thee to muſe,</l>
               <l>This <hi>World,</hi> forſook me ſtreight;</l>
               <l>And, ever ſince, doth me abuſe.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Hate</hi> and <hi>Scornes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her <hi>Love</hi> ſhe turns;</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Friends,</hi> my <hi>Foes</hi> ſhe makes:</l>
               <l>What <hi>ſland'rous Lies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She can deviſe,</l>
               <l>Of me, ſhe faines, and ſpeakes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> And, now, with Vaunts and <hi>Brags,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That, ſhe, on me, <hi>aveng'd</hi> appears;</l>
               <l>From me, her <hi>gaudy Rags,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With all her <hi>Gifts,</hi> away ſhe tears:</l>
               <l>And not content</l>
               <l>So to have rent</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116015:35"/>
               <l>What was by <hi>her beſtown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She would bereave</l>
               <l>(With what ſhe gave)</l>
               <l>Thoſe things, that are <hi>mine own.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> She doth corrupt my <hi>Friends,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Wrongs and Sorrows to increaſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>Comforters</hi> ſhe ſends,</l>
               <l>To make more grievous my <hi>Diſtreſs:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To mind ſhe calls,</l>
               <l>Things <hi>true</hi> and <hi>falſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which may my <hi>Peace</hi> impair;</l>
               <l>With whatſoe'er,</l>
               <l>May make me fear,</l>
               <l>And, let in <hi>Black Deſpair.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Not thoſe <hi>Defects</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>For which, ſhe justly me ſuſpects,</l>
               <l>(Or <hi>Duties</hi> left undone,)</l>
               <l>To my <hi>Vexation,</hi> ſhe objects;</l>
               <l>But, doth deviſe</l>
               <l>How, ſhe likewiſe</l>
               <l>May to my blame pervert,</l>
               <l>What I deſign'd</l>
               <l>With upright minde,</l>
               <l>And <hi>ſingleneſs of heart.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:116015:36"/>
            <lg>
               <l n="8">
                  <hi>8.</hi> And, (which augments my care)</l>
               <l>My <hi>Selfneſs</hi> oft with her conſpires,</l>
               <l>Which ere I am aware</l>
               <l>Lets in falſe Fears, and vain deſires;</l>
               <l>Which, taking part</l>
               <l>Againſt my Heart,</l>
               <l>Therein ſuch Tumults make,</l>
               <l>That, ſometimes, they</l>
               <l>Bear <hi>Spoiles</hi> away,</l>
               <l>And, cauſe my <hi>Faith</hi> to ſhake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="9">
                  <hi>9.</hi> Yet this affrights me more,</l>
               <l>Then all their <hi>Malice, Force</hi> or <hi>Guile;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou, though I Thee implore,</l>
               <l>Stand'ſt by, as <hi>Newter,</hi> all the while.</l>
               <l>What ſhe hath done</l>
               <l>Thou look'ſt upon,</l>
               <l>And, knowſt what they intend;</l>
               <l>Yet letst them ſtill</l>
               <l>Purſue their Will,</l>
               <l>As if Thou wert her <hi>Friend.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="10">
                  <hi>10.</hi> Oh! <hi>whither,</hi> or to <hi>whom</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can I for Health or Comfort fly?</l>
               <l>If Thou, my <hi>Foe</hi> become,</l>
               <l>Whereon, henceforth, ſhall I rely?</l>
               <l>I hope may have</l>
               <l>That in the Grave</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116015:36"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Immortal Life</hi> may be;</l>
               <l>And finde as well</l>
               <l>A <hi>Heav'n</hi> in <hi>Hell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Joy</hi> in ought ſave <hi>Thee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="11">
                  <hi>11.</hi> But, LORD, though in the dark,</l>
               <l>And in contempt, thy ſervant lies;</l>
               <l>On me there ſhines a <hi>Spark</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Loving-kindneſs</hi> from Thine eyes:</l>
               <l>Yea, though without</l>
               <l>(Quite round about)</l>
               <l>I am inclos'd with <hi>Sin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Increaſing <hi>Foes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fears, Wars</hi> and <hi>Woes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou, Peace</hi> preſerv'ſt <hi>within.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l n="12">
                  <hi>12.</hi> For, when I looked on</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Terrors</hi> which begirt me round,</l>
               <l>I thought, Thou had'ſt been gone,</l>
               <l>Becauſe no outward <hi>Hope</hi> I found.</l>
               <l>Yet hid <hi>Thou</hi> wert</l>
               <l>Within my Heart,</l>
               <l>Still preſent, all the while,</l>
               <l>And my late <hi>Fear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth falſe appear:</l>
               <l>For, now I ſee Thee <hi>Smile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116015:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
